no better good afternoon everyone
so just a few announcements
it's you know web bureaus been out there
it's due this Thursday there are no wait
days no greatest days no excuses so
don't put it off to the last minute oh
it should be everything set you should
be able to do it lab one became
available sometime there only this
morning and we're starting with web one
the way we're going to release the
information we need to do though is
through this website called the project
zone which will guide you through the
write-up and require you to answer some
little simple questions along the way is
our way of encouraging you to read the
write on carefully and only once you get
through that you'll get a little code
now you can actually start the web and
do all the work of the web because
you'll be able to get the files actually
for it
Vado and directly but to see the right
out the end to actually submit it to
auto web you'll have to have this little
passkey that comes at the end of your
completion of the right up through the
project so and then you'll put that in
the file and submit that as part of your
handle so that's all described but
there's a suit of two-phase part that
there's the project zone there's Auto
labs oh oh
this particular lab is we'll make use of
what you learned last week and this week
about bits bytes and numeric
representations and so in particular a
good chunk of the problems are just bit
level manipulation questions that the
material in the lecture material for it
will be from last week and from today
and then on Thursday we'll talk about
floating-point and that will cover all
the information then next Monday will be
your first recitation class and it will
talk about that quite a bit more but I'd
recommend you get started before next
Monday on this way question over there
yeah lab theorem is not required in lab
one by the way I'm not sure if Auto atom
is working quite right yet on it start
submission so if you really out early
and you want to submit it today might
not work we're tracking that down oh but
you can certainly get started on the web
as it is this and also mention and I'll
say this in the various other place this
particular lab has more kind of quirks
and bumps and works in the software then
I feel good about and the reason is
because we've kind of patched together
this odd mix of software to support how
we do the checking of your code for its
conformance to some programming rules
and correctness and things that it's
trying to meet Mike very swimsuit of odd
aspects of it that are all documented in
the write-up but it's easy to overlook
that when you're first skimming through
so this is one of these things before
you run off to Piazza and ask what do
you mean about this or what do you mean
about that or I get the following weird
error report please re-read the write-up
several times because a lot of times all
of a sudden it will jump out at you that
you have arrived oh right curly brace
and the first column to finish your
function definitions that aren't part of
the normal seat programming conventions
so today we're going to continue talking
about the representation of values in
particular integer values
as bit and we started that last time and
what we'll do is is continue that today
talking about the different arithmetic
operations you want to perform landfills
will also cover some more general than
students how information is stored in
memory and how its referenced oh so you
recall from before that the two
equations that you really have to know
and understand and everything else
follows from those two equations it's
given a set of bits what number does
that represent and we can talk about
that number is either a unsigned integer
meaning its value is either 0 or greater
or the other representation we'll look
at in this class is two's complement
representation which allows you to have
numbers that are both negative and
positive and the way that works is by
simply making the most significant death
they have a negative value to it so that
if it's set then it in turn makes the
number very negative and then you can
add back some more bits positive bits to
bring it back closer to zero and so we
looked at the example and here's the
correct version of it that 10 is simply
2 plus 8 but - town is is minus 16 plus
4 plus 2 so you start with minus 16 you
add back 4 that gives you minus 12 add
back to that gives you minus 10 I should
also mention two's complement there's
nothing in the c standard in fact the c
standard is very careful not to say thou
shalt use two's complement numbers but
the x86 processors which is what we use
and really just about every processor
that you're likely to come across does
use two's complement so you can't always
assume this when you're writing programs
but for the platforms that we're
interested in this will be the case and
so we talked about this idea that
there's a sort of correspondence between
unsigned and signed numbers
that's based on this kind of odd idea
that when you convert from one to the
other you actually don't do anything you
keep the bits in there whatever pattern
they are and you just change your
interpretation of what those bits me
so for these are 4-bit values so as an
unsigned number it can range from 0 to
15 but as a two's complement number it
can range from minus 8 to positive 7 and
you'll notice that for the positive case
the place where these two
representations overlap they match but
for the cases where they don't what is a
very large number a relatively large
number is an unsigned becomes a negative
number as a sign number but any time a
program in C casts or for some reason
sort of switches between unsigned and
signed representations that's what it's
doing is nothing it's just changing what
numeric value is assigned to a
particular bit pattern and that has it's
sort of strange and quirky behaviors to
it and the other that I mentioned last
time it is especially peculiar is if you
have an operation say addition or less
than and one of the operands is signed
and the other is unsigned the rule in C
is and this is the C standard is
there'll be an implicit conversion from
that sign value to an unsigned value and
then whatever operation would be
performed is performed Oh
last time we also talked about this idea
of sign extension which is to take a
smaller bit pattern and make it larger
you do it by copying the most
significant bit into the new positions
and what we saw with that is for the
case of this is for a two's complement
number what it does is it gives you a
larger number of bits this represents
the exact same number similarly if you
want to shrink a number of what happens
is they do
chop off the high-order bits in whatever
if it's a signed number whatever used to
be in this what's the new most
significant fit position that becomes
assigned it and that may or may not be a
good idea in terms of preserving numeric
values obviously if you're going to
shrink the number of bits some values
will be unrepresentable and that's
becomes the consequence of this but
that's just the way it works
so now let's poke into arithmetic
operations and we'll see the same
general ideas apply that and usually
it's a little more intuitive to
understand the unsigned case than the
sine case so the idea with unsigned
addition is in principle if you want to
add two numbers each say of n bits that
to fully represent the sum of those two
numbers you might need n plus 1 bits and
it's a little hard if you keep adding
numbers to go and get more bits and so
what happens is we just chop it off and
say whatever the extra bit was I'm going
to ignore the so-called overflow bit
whether it was a 0 or 1 I'm not going to
do it and the effect of that is it is
sort of a modular arithmetic that that
the additions are just wraps around and
continues on so for example this example
shows if I add the numbers a decimal 223
to 213 if I had enough bits I'd get the
number 446 what I don't I'm going to
keep it at 8 bits and so I'm going to
just chop off that most significant bit
and the result I'll get is 190 you might
notice is exactly 256 smaller than 446
and that's the effect because he can
think of here that we're dropping off
that bit there that we're dropping has
weight or value 256 and so by
eliminating that what we're doing is
decreasing the result by 256
and so actually and this is part of the
seed guarantees that all addition will
be performed as modular addition so even
when it overflows the program is
completely well specified behavior of
what it's supposed to do so if I think
of the possible range of values that
these numbers could have along the x and
y axes and then the sum of the values on
the z then the sort of normal addition
would give you this plain diagonal plane
because once sort of the definition of a
linear function but if I go to two's
complement addition I'm sorry to
unsigned addition what you see is it
sort of splits into these two regions
each of a chance of plane and the first
the left hands apart shows where it's oh
by the way I'm gonna try this hold you
did today
this part here I'll show is where it's
the true sum of the numbers but over on
the right here where it would've kept
going up instead what I've done is I've
chopped off that low significant bit
this is 4-bit addition the air so
chopped off the value of 16 and now what
this left is is the the original sum
minus 16 and so that will climb up in
this case as high as 14 so as the
picture on the left shows you can think
of when you do the overflow then you're
shifting the the sum back down into the
range of the original set of numbers
so for two's complement addition card
the reason why it's the commonly used
technique is the hardware is the same
the actual low-level addition operation
is exactly the same for we simply add
the two numbers and throw away any extra
bits that might overflow and call that
result the sum and so is he and this is
an important thing to understand is that
whether you you say it's a sum of two
minutes or a son of two unsigned the
actual bit level of behavior is the same
and again you can see that here with the
same set of bit patterns as before but
now since this is a two's complement
number that if you woke on the right
you'll see that these bit patterns
represent the numbers minus 23 and minus
43 a respectively if you were to just
add those numbers you'd get as just bit
you get 446 which doesn't seem to make
much sense but if you chop off that most
significant bit you'll see that what you
have left is the bit pattern for minus
66 which is exactly what you'd expect
turns out if you really want to do two's
complement addition and add the extra
bits I should have sign extended it to
be a nine bit numbers and then done the
addition and then it would have come
back up here so it's this is a little
bit of a peculiar example but you see
that the result is this idea that now
the remaining eight bit number
represents minus 66 so again you can
think of what happens is let me jump to
this picture well no I'll go through
this picture so now there's actually two
overflow cases what can happen is if you
take two numbers and add
and each of them is w bid then if you
look at the actual that what I'll call
the true some the sort of mathematical
sum of those two numbers you have three
different cases what is it that that
result is within the representable range
of the W bitties come with number in
which case that's the result you'll get
but if the number is too big then it's
called a positive overflow and what
we'll see is it will convert it into a
negative result and then the other is if
the number is too small being too
negative then you have what's called a
negative overflow and the resulting
number will end up having a positive
value so we can visualize it using the
same ideas before that this Center
region are the sort of non overflow
cases they're the ones where the sum of
these two numbers was within the range I
could represent as a 4-bit two's
complement number and the numbers that
the sum would have been to negative are
on the left they become positive and the
K numbers that were too large to
positive on the right become negative
numbers so that shows those two cases
this is all by the way you know if you
look at the formulas it all makes sense
and once you get used to this idea it
becomes very routine but if it's the
first time you've ever been confronted
with this it might be fairly
non-intuitive and the only way I can
advise you is look at exact little
examples of 4 bit numbers try adding
them together see what you get compare
that to the various formulas check them
out that you have to kind of let this
stuff bake inside of you to really fully
appreciate so if I look sort of a bird's
eye view from the top of that this
picture here you can see that there's
sort of three regions
if I for for consideration the the white
region here is the case where the
there's no overflow so that the sum of
the two numbers is representable within
the range of the result and so that's
and then the two pink ones are the
overflow cases and you can see that
first of all if you're adding numbers of
opposite signs you see you can never get
an overflow because you'll take a
negative number and a positive number
and you'll end up somewhere in between
so it's guaranteed to be representable
so the danger is by adding two positive
numbers that becomes too big or two
negative numbers that become too small
those are the two possible over four
cases and as it shows these two
represent these Vil of trying the older
regions and also as the formula shows
here when you do have negative overflow
then it becomes a positive number it has
the effect of adding the value two to
the W to the sum and similarly if it's a
positive overflow it becomes a negative
number that you can think of as
subtracting to you the don't you from
that boy so I think the only example
here was one that didn't overflow that's
a if you want to do it the bit level
you'd have to take some other examples
okay so that's addition and I should
mention by the way again if we just go
strictly by the C programming standards
they don't they guarantee that unsigned
arithmetic is always modular but they
don't guarantee what happens if you
overflow they're positive or negative
with signed addition so if you're really
really strict and careful about how you
do C programming you should guard
against
like that again in practice it's these
two's complement representation so
there's a very predictable behavior of
overflow or underflow overflow either
positive or negative but it might not be
what you want so but you can at least
predict what it is so multiplication is
a little bit Messier again and this big
pile of stuff what it basically shows it
if I have two numbers that are each W
bits and I multiply them then I should
need twice as many bits if I want to
safely represent the product and that
result holds for both the unsigned case
and for the toothed countersign case and
basically you can take the largest
number you represent you square that and
that will require 2 2 times W bits to
represent um but again we don't have
arbitrary we can't just keep adding bits
to our numbers in general to do this and
so what happens is we just truncate the
result
so for example with unsigned if you had
two operands U and V and you multiply
them you might need twice the number of
bits to represent the true product that
sort of mathematical product of those
two numbers but we'll just drop off
those upper bits and just leave the
results within this W good range and
again it you can see that this is
exactly an implementation of modular
arithmetic and modular arithmetic is
something that's maybe not the standard
multiplication but it's one that people
know and understand very well so again
if I took my two numbers 226 and 213 and
multiply them I'd get forty-seven
thousand four hundred ninety-nine which
is too big to represent it than eight
bits so I just chop off those upper bits
and I get 221 which is the mod 256
product of these two numbers sign
multiplication is a little bit trickier
actually it turns out it turns out that
to actually when you do two's complement
multiplication again you should use your
product will be twice at number of bits
and if you look at the bits they'll
actually be different then they work for
the unsigned case so look at the example
here you will see that to multiply these
two numbers to negative numbers you get
the positive result 1989 and it's bit
level representation looks like so zeros
and if I go back and look at the same
bit pattern being multiplied as an
unsigned number you'll see a different
bit pattern to these puckering bits on
the other hand if you look at the lower
8 bits 1 0 1 1 0 1 and 1 1 0 1 you'll
see that's the same for both the signed
in the unsigned case 1 1 0 1 1 1 0 1 and
so and this actually an important rule
is that the lower part of the product
which is typically the only part that
you keep is the same whether it's a sign
the trees compliment multiplication or
an unsigned multiplication the upper
bits can differ but it's relatively
seldom that you actually want the full
certain twice the size a product of two
numbers so for example an x86 there's
some special instructions you have to do
to get that product the normal multiply
instruction only gives you the lower 32
or 64 bits then it takes a special
instruction to get a full 64-bit product
of two 32-bit numbers or 120
product of two 64-bit numbers and so so
most of the time then the fact that the
lower parts of the bits are the same is
good enough to say okay I'm going to use
the same multiply instructions for both
cases and and we'll see with x86
actually have two different instructions
for doing the larger version of
multiplication when you need the full
representation so one of the things
you'll see one of the things we do in
this course that's kind of unusual is
that we look at when you will write C
code and then look at where the compiler
spits out when it compiles that code and
one of the realities that you have to
deal with and doing that is looking at
code that the compiler has done some
optimizations that you have to learn
what those optimizations really means
and so an example of that is any time in
C you have an expression that involves
multiplying by a constant and especially
if that constant is a power of two then
it won't actually the compiler would
actually stick a multiply instruction in
there stick in a shift and the reason is
that if you want to multiply by a power
of two you can do that by just shifting
the number left the appropriate number
of bit positions so if I want to
multiply a number by 2 to the K but then
all I have to do is shift that number
left by cave or positions and you
remember the shift always has the effect
of filling in on the right with the
zeros and dropping off any bits that
fall off the end so both of those cases
even when it instead of overflows as a
result it's still preserving the that
same arithmetic behavior is a multiply
instruction and you can think of it
again if you think about how these
numbers remember if it's a
we'll just think of unsigned for now all
when we shift that number up what we're
doing is each bit now has a weight
that's 2 to the K greater than would
have if it hadn't stayed in its original
position and so we're giving all these
bits sort of an extra boost and that has
the effect of multiplying the whole
number by 2 to the cap and again the
rule says whether it's signed you're
unsigned we can just drop those any bits
that get shifted out and we'll get the
same effect as if we done the sort of
regular bit level multiplication
operation so for example if we shift a
number left by 3 it's the same as
multiplying it by 8 and you can put
together various combinations of these
like if you shift a number left by 5
that's the same as multiplying by 32 and
then you subtract off shifting that same
number left by 3 so that's like
multiplying by 8 so it's 32 minus 8 is
24 that's the same effect as as
multiplying the original number by 24
and you can see it can mix and match
these because addition or multiplication
distributes over addition it has even in
this sort of strange world of two's
complement numbers and unsigned numbers
in modular arithmetic it has that same
set of arithmetic properties and so even
if there's overflows or
funny things that happen this this
equality is still the exact same and
that's why the compiler can safely
replace a multiplied by two shifts in an
ad and get be sure that no matter what
the number is it will have the same
result and it depends actually it
depends on the hardware whether that's a
good idea or not is to three addition
the three are two shifts in a
subtraction faster or slower than a
multiplication that actually depends on
how fast you multiply it
and how fast it can perform the other
instructions and then uh I think the
processors you'll find today it's about
uh about what dead heat is on those two
they're pretty close to each other but
and the compiler doesn't actually know
much about you real hardware it's just
moving a guess but it will typically do
these kind of substitutions questions
yes if it's well if it's unsigned
unsigned arithmetic is guaranteed to be
like modular arithmetic both
multiplication the other districts sign
numbers right just like addition there's
no the standard does not specify
ass-kisser i have to kind of keep
reminding myself of this because i've
gotten a bit sloppy at time so say it's
just to accomplish I know how that looks
Oh so here's another trick that's kind
of an interesting one and if you like
this kind of stuff and that actually is
very useful to is if you want to divide
by a power of two you can do that by
shifting as well and for the unsigned
case it's very straightforward if you
want to divide by tooth decay you just
shift the number right by K bits and
this can be pretty useful if you want a
scale like you want to ask how many
bytes
how many given some of them are bytes
how many double precision numbers can I
stick in there you want to divide it by
eight well you just take that original
number and shift it right by three
positions so that gives you the answer
so in
unsigned we can do this using the
logical shift which he recall fills in
with zeros and
again the sudo logic behind this is as I
mentioned I think last lecture we can
think of them of a bit level
representation even including fractional
numbers but no longer do we have a
decimal point what we have is a binary
point and the numbers to the right in
the binary point have fractional values
1/2 1/4 1/8 1/16 so if we shift a number
by K it's like moving the the first
though we significant K bits to the
right of the binary point which now all
has fractional value and sums to
something less than 1 so if I just now
throw those bits away
what I'm doing is rounding that number
down to the nearest integer which is
exactly what you want for for division
so just to illustrate that with some
examples you see that if I take the
number 15 to 13 if I were to divide that
by 2 I get a fractional number of 76 so
six point five but I want to round
toward zero in this case and so if I
just drop off that point five
I'll get seventy six so six which is
what I want and similarly if I take 15
to 13 and divide it by 16 I end up with
a number that 915 point eight one two
five which I want to round toward zero
to 950 and so you can see that that
shifting just discarding any extra bits
as the desired behavior of rounding
toward zero for two's complement numbers
you almost get the same result by
shifting using an arithmetic shift and
that's why the arithmetic shift is there
oh the only problem is it doesn't quite
do the wrong thing the right thing with
negative
so let's see if I can give an example so
that the ideas is saying that we
remember an arithmetic shift we fill in
with by copying the most significant bit
over and over again so you can imagine
for positive numbers it's just the same
as what we saw before for negative
numbers you see that it doesn't quite do
the right thing so for example if I take
minus 15 to 13 and I divide it by 2
again minus sixty seventy six over six
point five now if I just throw away
these tips here the problem is those
bits had a positive value and so what
I'm actually doing is decreasing this
number what they call brown bits or
minus infinity I'm rounding it to a more
negative number which in this case was
minus mu 607 and so where you see this
minus nine fifteen point eight one two
five it's rounded to minus 951 if I just
do the ship on its own I don't do
anything else so it's not quite right
it's off by one basically for all these
negative cases I want to round to zero
so I want around positive numbers down
negative number is up so the trick is
and what you'll see the compiler does is
to basically take the case of a negative
number and bias it by adding a little
bit to it
before you it performs a shift and that
little bit that it adds will be just
enough to kind of tip it and make it
round in the right direction and the the
way it does that then is by adding this
bias of see if I can show
let me just show in the picture by
adding the number that's actually to the
K minus one which is a number that has
all one's for the these lowest cave-ins
and what that has the effect of doing is
when I add that is I will if this
original number was all zeros which is
what's shown here and I am a bunch of
ones to there nothing's going to happen
I mean it would only end up with all
ones but this yellow part will stay the
same as before and when I shift that and
drop off anything is right in the binary
point then then I'll get back just the
original shifted number and you'll see
I'm doing an arithmetic shift I'm
filling it with once so for the case
where no rounding is required then it
what this shows is it does this biasing
is no real effect but for the case where
I needed to do that a little bit of
rounding what happens is by adding this
bias in here if there are any one bits
in all to the right of the binary point
of what will become the binary point
then then this value will cause an
incremented value in the yellow portion
and then when I shift that to the right
what I'll get is effectively
incrementing by one this number which
gets my bias right so this is it
probably easy as it's understood by
example this is the best understood by
example and I don't have one handy so
but so this is a pretty quick march
through it the book covers this with
some
actual examples and I recommend you look
at those but this is a again so it turns
out that this is always a good idea for
the compiler if it can get away with a
shift instead of divide that's a big
savings because divide is a relatively
expensive operation even on a modern
processor on the other hand whereas I
could mix and match these I could divide
x 24 using two shifts in a subtraction
you see it doesn't really work when you
want to divide by something other than a
power of two you can't sort of break
that up into a bunch of separate power
of two cases so this is really only
useful for the special case of dividing
by a power too but you'll see this in in
real life code so just a few other
tricks of the trade one is when I took a
course in logic design many years ago I
learned this trick for computing the
negation of a number in two's complement
form when they call complement plus
increment so we've got examples yeah so
for example if I wanted to complement
the number 1 5 203 or increment negator
you see that's its binary representation
so if I complement that if I take all
the bits and just bit by bit put the
opposite value in that's complementing
it and you see numerically that
represents the value - 15 - 14 and the
intuition of why that's true is if you
add X and it's complement you'll get a
number that's all wands which of course
you recall is the representation of
negative 1 and so we can see that the
number X questions compliment is is
minus 1 and therefore if I now add a 1
back to this complement his number I'll
get minus X so if I now increment that
in this case it was an even number so I
just said that Victor that one then this
will be the value of minus 15 to 30 so
that's a pretty handy trick and again
all of these really you know there's not
some magic new knowledge here it's they
all stem back to that original formula
showing what the numeric value is of a
two's complement number and so some
special cases like four zero if I
complement it I'll get all ones which is
minus one so if I add back a one to that
I'll come back to zero and one of the
interesting numbers is if I complement
it is T min if I complement it I should
get T Max and if I add 1 to t max what
do I get
I'll get Tina back so I took the most
positive number and I added 1 to it and
I got the most angry but that's what
they call positive overflow yeah
and so what you can see is actually if
you give a compute the expression minus
X and X is T then you'll get back team
it just like if t minus 0 is 0 4 minus T
min is team in in two's complement in
the world of two's complement which by
the way whenever any question comes up
is this behavior always true or false
usually you want to test the special
cases is 0 and T min to see because
they're often the counter example to any
general rules so just to summarize that
part then actually what I'm gonna I'm
going to summarize it but we're about to
do our quiz and so if you want to start
working you
way into canvas oh yeah because I know
it takes some time with all your
I'm trying to figure out how to get to
canvas are you guys taking this quiz you
probably ahead of me out I can't
okay let's see how we've done this sorry
it took me so long
okay so I'd say people generally did
pretty well here so actually the answer
to the first problem was already stated
in lecture when you have two numbers
with opposite signs they can never
overflow remember I said if it's a
positive number and a negative number
you're adding them together you'll end
up somewhere in between most people
about that everyone basically got the
idea that shifting left by four is the
same as multiplying by sixteen not
remember this a left shift
not a right shift and how many values to
see have four faults instead of a trick
question in that remember false as one
value which is zero true is anything
that's nonzero this one actually was I
can see that people didn't necessarily
guess the answer on this and so will
actually cover that in just a second but
this is good I think this is very useful
information so I think a lot of people
recalled from last time this example of
a MOOC with a an unsigned loop index I
and the problem with this is that if I
is since I is let me stir the soup
since I is unsigned it will always be
greater than or equal to zero and so
this group test is useless and it can be
a little more subtle as people saw if
Delta is sizeof int Delta is defined to
be an unsigned number until by the rules
we had this would be cast to unsigned
and therefore always be greater or equal
to zero so the particular quiz problem
if this works what it was doing is
instead of using size of int it had a
particular hex number I think it was
four eight right for the way I can
change this and so I think some of you
said whoa hex numbers that looks kind of
unsigned to me and so you guessed that
that would also be an unsigned number
which is not a bad guess but it's wrong
in this case since four there's actually
a pretty complicated set of rules that
when you write it some digits out what
datatype does that imply and in fact if
you really want to get into this there's
a web aside for the book that you can
get to off of the court the books web
page that says how do I write T min and
it goes through the whole conversion
rules which are really inque
arcane it actually depends on which
version of C you use so this could be a
very
complicated answer but the simple
version is if the number can be
represented as an INT and there is no
little u next to it it will be treated
as a hint
and so hex 4 is the same as decimal 4 in
this case it will be an assigned number
and so since I in this example the
example is very similar to this one will
be all this will be done using signed
arithmetic so the people got that wrong
it wasn't a fundamental misunderstanding
it's just this is one kind of corner of
the sea rules that we didn't even cover
and aren't often covered in any standard
presentations good so I used to counsel
people I'd say well if you're gonna
count down then don't use unsigned
arithmetic because it will get you in
trouble and there's a fella day I don't
think he's there anymore but used to
work at the software engineering
Institute who sent me email saying by
the way you gave really bad advice so
this guy named Robert Secord has written
a set of books about what he calls
secure coding and if you really want to
be a super careful programmer it's a
pretty interesting about collection of
books he has it in C C++ is ones in Java
and so forth and he's especially he's a
a computer security person so he's
trying to say how can you write code
that on any compiler on any system is
less prone to being attacked or
vulnerable have bugs and so what he
claims is that the best way to do
counting down then is to use a unsigned
value as you loop index but then rather
than checking is it greater than or
equal to zero you actually check is it
less than your starting value because
the logic behind it you keep going until
that happens because what happens is
once I goes
to zero then the next thing it will
become is it will wrap around and become
you max because it's unsigned arithmetic
is guaranteed you be modular on any
machine on any compiler so you're
guaranteed once it goes below zero or
apparently blows you or when it's really
good to go is up to a really big notice
and so that's a very non-intuitive
looking loop writing scheme is to put
instead of greater than or equal to 0
you saying less than count and I've
started using this in my own programming
and once you kind of get used to it it
looks reasonable but at first it seemed
like a very strange thing and he even
recommends instead of declaring it as an
unsigned that you declared as this
datatype size T which is depending on
the Machine type is always sort of a big
enough number to handle the the full
word size of your machine 32 or 64 bits
so that's um just one piece of advice
I'll pass along to you from Richard
Roberts II court so other uses of
unsigned as I mentioned if you really
really want to be careful the good news
about on site is it does have a complete
specification of what to do even in
overflow cases and often modular
arithmetic is actually fairly useful if
you want to do multiple position
arithmetic you saw when you were doing
set operations it's sort of natural just
to think of a bit says bit flags and no
sort of negative numbers involved and
you'll find in systems programming when
you talk about addresses or masks you
know collections of bits and things
unsigned is a fairly sort of a
reasonable thing to conceptually so it's
interesting like Java does not have
unsigned numbers but it has because they
didn't want to get into all these quirks
but in C unsigned numbers it kind of
bill
and they're very ease okay just to
finish it up then let's talk about how
we can layout collections of bytes in
memory and when we look at the actual
machine code assembly code you'll see
that it's issuing all these addresses
and people ask well where's where's the
memory and the answer is well
conceptually the memory just exists it's
called virtual memory and it's fist you
can think of it conceptually it's just a
big array of bytes from over a wide
range of addresses physically what
happens is the combination of hardware
and soft system software makes that
virtual memory real by using some
combination of of caches of actual DRAM
on typical machine or and even on the
disks or solid-state drives that built
into your machine or even over the
network potentially so instead of
providing that memory and swapping it in
and trying to make it look like it's all
really there even if it isn't so anyways
but from a machine level programming we
don't think about all that memory
hierarchy we just think of it as in
terms of virtual memory so you can just
think of it as a big array of buttons
and in fact when you're running multiple
programs on the machine on the same
machine they each have their own
separate collection range of virtual
addresses and what that means is if
you're running multiple programs and
actually buy one won't directly affect
the behavior of another and that's a
good thing because if if one program
misbehaves it's kind of got a bug it
can't make but the rest of the programs
crash by just doing all right to some
memory location so that's sometimes
referred to as a process when you
have the processes the execution of a
program
on a machine and you can have one
program that's that which there's
multiple processes running that same
program so each process and each
executing program has its own virtual
address space and you'll often hear
people talk about word size as I
mentioned in the first class there's no
real solid definition of what the word
is on a machine we talk about 32-bit
machines and 64-bit machines but most
machines that your laptops your phones
and most desktop machines nowadays are
actually can run code either compiled
for 32-bit execution or for 64-bit
execution so it's really a combination
of the hardware and the compiled code
that defines what word sizes but in
general for a machine the sort of
broadest concept of a word is how big
are the addresses in that machine so and
as I mentioned that can actually depend
on the mode of the program the machine
is executed so a 32-bit machine means
that its largest addresses to the 31 is
32 minus 1 and that's roughly 4
gigabytes the Machine set even phones
nowadays are mostly running 64-bit
processors and what that means is in
principle an address can be as many 64
bits and that would give you an address
range of something bigger like 10 to the
19th bytes which is a lot of bytes by
the way an exabyte so you think of the
biggest disk drive you can buy nowadays
is I don't know 8 terabytes or maybe
bigger but that's still a thousand times
smaller than addressable range so to
really support a full 64 bit
memory space he made a machine would say
a thousand disk drives just even have
that many bits of memories somewhere so
what happens is on on the machines that
they actually don't today the hardware
it's not only 64-bit addresses but they
only like to use the first 48 of those
and so they don't really support to
64-bit execution anyways the point being
that depending on how big your words are
that defines how many bytes of memory
you can address and the general rule
then is if I have a multi byte quantity
what's its address what's defined to be
the lowest numbered byte in in in its
collection of four bytes so will
represent a a 32 bit quantity is 4 bytes
and the address of that 32 bit quantity
will be the that we significant or not
the leasing of the byte with the lowest
number to dress and similarly for other
senses and as I mentioned last for some
previous lecture we've seen this slide
before that depending on whether you're
executing a 32-bit program or a 64-bit
program some of the data types will
change and particularly a pointer an
address will change between being a four
byte quantity or an eight by quantity so
there's one thing that's left here is if
I have multiple bytes representing a
value what order should they be
interpretive to the addresses and
there's two obvious conventions one is
you put them in from least significant
to both and the other is from most to
least and as you can imagine in any case
where there's a choice where then some
people choose one way and some people
choose the other and so that's sometimes
referred to as the byte ordering and
it's commonly called big endian vs.
little endian byte ordering and that's a
term
that goes back to the book Gulliver's
Travels even though that was written
long before there were bytes to store in
a computer and there was a fellow who
wrote a kind of amusing tale about how
people were fighting about this byte
ordering the way the characters in this
book had fought over which end of a egg
should you opened anyways nowadays it
turns out that you're gonna live in a
little Indian world if it's an x86
hardware and that remember that applies
to Windows OS X and to Linux it's gonna
be little endian an ARM processor like
as in most earphones can actually run
and eat the hardware can run with either
byte ordering but when you're running
any of the common operating systems it
will be little endian ordering so little
endian means that the least significant
bites come first and there's a few
machines that you're less likely to
encounter that are big endian but one of
the annoying things some reason when
they're designing the internet protocols
they said whoever was in charge said I
want big endian than they did it so when
you send packets over the internet what
has to happen and you'll see that when
you write this code you have to use
special functions to convert the byte
ordering going out to the network and
coming back in so what do I mean by this
so again assume we had a value that we
wrote in hex a 1 2 3 4 byte value which
we'd write when we write it of course
like up above we put the most
significant byte on the left and the
least significant byte on the right but
now when we go that into memory will see
that in big endian order if we read from
left
it looks the same because the most
significant the least significant byte
is at the highest address the most
significant is that the lowest address
but if we write it in little-endian
ordering and appears to be reversed I
remember these conventions of how you
read things list things left to right is
just a convention that's not really the
point being the address the lowest
numbered address has either the most
significant byte or the least
significant byte but we'll find in the
real world since we're going to live in
a little Indian world most in time that
we're often looking at things written
backwards with the byte order reversed
so there used to be machines actually on
campus made by a company called Sun
Microsystems which was later acquired by
Oracle and they're still making these
machines but they're not very common at
least sort of outside of the world of
database machines but so I could
actually run these experiments and see
you know their verify what order you get
when you listed various numbers in
ascending order
and so if 15 to 13 has a hex
representation freebie 16 on an x86
machine you'll see that we significant
bytes is 60 and then the next one is 3b
and then it's two zeros and on one of
these Sun machines you'd see it reversed
order and on a 64-bit machine would be
in a little endian machine by the 8 byte
for a long
and you can actually write code and
there's code actually included in the
code for today's lecture that lets you
sort of print out the byte
representation of different data types
by just sort of walking through them one
button at a time and printing out each
byte value and you can run it on on
various different things and get numbers
like this is 15 to 13 printed on a Linux
machine and you'll see it's a little
endian machine unfortunately I don't
know any machines on campus that at
least I have an account on that it's a
big endian machine there might be
somewhere in the accounting department
but not and I don't think even there and
another point that this slide makes his
pointers are simply addresses they're
just you can think of it as an index
into this array of the virtual memory
but where they're located where
particular dress is located depends on
the Machine the operating system the
compiler a bunch of different things and
so from one machine one execution to
another
pointers might change values they don't
have any sort of uniform representation
us and then another important part is
strings at least in C are always
represented by just a sequence of single
byte values in the so-called ASCII
format where the final bite then is zero
and that's completely independent of
byte ordering because it's a on a byte
by byte basis so in fact when you're
writing software that that has to be
compatible across machines one thing
people often do is instead of encoding
numbers in binary and worrying about
byte ordering they encode them as
you know numerix as strings send a
string convert back to a numeric
representation so for example one of the
things you'll start doing in the next
wave is will staring at a lot of
disassembled code its assembly it's
really machine code written in a
somewhat human readable format and
you'll see you know x86 machine that all
the numbers are written
apparently backwards and it's annoying
because it's not really backwards it's
sort of a backwards on of with pairs of
hex digits so one to a B becomes a b12
okay let's just finish up with a not
online quiz without just some questions
and again these are first of all really
great exam problems but also good ways
to kind of make you think through the
implications of some of these ideas in a
lot of this we've all we've sort of
looked at in various forms so and the
answer to these is either yes it's true
or no there's at least one case one
value of x for which this is not true
and in the latter case it's good to be
able to give an example so if X is less
than 0 is 2 X less than 0
no not x squared is x times 2 and by the
way as I mentioned T min is always a
good counter example generators yes yes
so if it depends then the answer is no
right
and can you give me an example
let's go team in that's a great example
right because team n if it's one zero
zero zero remember multiplying by 2 is
the same as shifting it left and so I'm
just gonna throw away that one so yes
you're right how about an unsigned
number UX is assumed these is sort of
arbitrary numbers is it always better
equal to zero yeah it's unsigned
okay this is getting more obscure if I
and this is a 32-bit number assume so if
I take the end of X and 7 and then I and
I see that at 7 and I shift that number
left by 30 is it going to be negative
what so what this means if you remember
7 as bit representation 7 looks like 1 1
1 right so X + 7 if I get 7 out of that
it means all the low 3 order the low 3
bits of X are ones and so if I shift it
left by 30 I'm guaranteed that these 2
bits will become the most significant
bits of that shifted result right and so
this bit in particular is a 1 and so the
result would be negative
so the answer to that is yes the reason
why involves a very specific parts of
that question right is you X greater
than minus 1 hmm so the answer is no but
it's not for the obvious reason right so
what's the counter example to this so
what first of all what will be anything
that is not the right answer that's the
non-intuitive part yes Tmax won't work
but you're getting closer you remember
if you X is an unsigned number so what
is first of all when I do this
comparison you remember from the last
lecture what will what will be the
comparison type will be a sign
comparison or Tuncer unsent very good
yeah yeah well no negative one is all
ones they're negative one is all ones
which becomes u Max and so this is
almost never this is this is actually
never true for any value of x you guys
but that's right the thing to remember
is o and unsigned assign convert them
both down so if X is greater than Y is
minus X less than minus y what would be
an example
of where this is wrong it's actually
almost true so you have to think of the
sort of less the common case where it's
wrong and what did I say about good
counter examples yes yes when Y is T
Mendes very good because when Y is T men
then minus y wallet so BT men right and
no number is less than that so anything
where Y is T men waterfalls very good is
x squared always greater equal to zero
actually I showed that in the first
lecture no 40,000 squared is not very
equal to zero in general you can have
over stories if x and y are both
positive will X plus y b+ no right
overflow case if X is greater equal to 0
well minus X be less than or equal 0
actually this one's true right but if X
is less than or equal to 0 well minus X
be greater equal to 0 what you guys are
catching on just use your friend T min
and you'll you'll keep going right if I
this is really obscure if I look at X
and minus X and I are those together and
shift it right by 31 well that equal
minus 1 this is arithmetic shift
what works routine end this actually
almost works can you give me one example
where it doesn't work zero
yes this might be a useful hint in one
of your puzzles command is shifting a
unsigned number right by three the same
as dividing it by eight yeah right it's
unsigned remember that was the point
unsigned you can just shift it for a
signed number well I think the shaking
heads from before were for this one no
because it might round the wrong
direction
okay this Yvette's and the other one is
so anyways very good I think you're
catching on to this point well we'll see
you next time