good afternoon everyone
[Applause]
welcome to the ball 2017 offering of 15
to 13 as well as 18 to 13 and there
might be a few students here from 15 5
13 as well so as you know this course
has three different numbers and there's
slight differences between the graduate
version 513 and the undergraduate
versions 213 but for the most part we
run this is one sort of monolithic
course one of the largest courses on
campus in fact and so this is of course
my name is Randy Bryant you might have
seen my name on the book that you've
bought or I was one of the first people
to teach this course many years ago and
I've taught it I'm not sure how many
times but a lot but I still really
enjoyed this course and I enjoy that the
students really find and get a lot out
of this course it means a lot to me and
to my co-author David Cameron who hasn't
been teaching this course of the last
several years the results were taught at
many times today I are two co
instructors as well
Phil Gibbons is also going to be giving
lectures just like I am and then Brian
reowing is nominally in charge of the
graduate of part of this course but
again we all work together in many
aspects of it so the first day I was
preparing lectures for this course about
when you were born
I typed in that number and I said I have
typed this number a lot of times 1 5 2 1
3 and that was known behold I got this
idea ah here's a tagline for the course
we have seen you exhibit I just hooked
up today 18 to 13 doesn't exist as an
area code and 15 5 15 is a somewhere in
Kansas so it doesn't really quite as
well there but it works great for for
Pittsburgh so today you know it's an
introductory but true so one thing is to
sort of do the big picture what's this
course about why are you in what we hope
you get from it what it will give you
for the future that kind of stuff where
did some of the major course themes and
then another part we're gonna do a
special discussion about academic
integrity because that's been a major
issue for this course and for other
courses in we try to address and bright
head-on as well as some topics about
logistics and policies so that's our
agenda from scale so um this course is
you know it's called introduction to
computer systems which is a kind of
bland in generic name but the idea of
this course is for the most part many of
you have sort of touched computers of
this somewhat abstract away you've
written code maybe in Python or other
languages where you're fairly far
removed from what's really going on into
the machine in terms of what bits are
being set what bytes are being stored
where is it being put what packets are
being sent across networks and things
and so the purpose of this course is to
kind of get you started on the road to
understanding more about what's really
inside that box and how it works and
there's a lot to be gained from that
just on its own and one of the things we
like about this course even if this is
the only systems course you ever take
your life you'll walk out of this course
with some very useful stuff that you can
apply to your job to your further
studies whatever your endeavors are
because yo you'll understand more you
know what quirky features are happening
when things out right how can I kind of
dig in and catch up some code to make
things work that wouldn't other work and
just that kind of stuff and then the
other part of this is for those of you
who go on and take other courses
particularly in computer science and ECE
in networking compilers operating
systems distributed systems computer
graphics embedded systems computer
architecture all those topics this
course is designed to sort of be the
your entre point and all those courses
over the years have have evolved to very
much build on the assumption that you've
mastered the material in this course for
them to get started in fact the origins
of this course was to help students get
ready for the operating systems of
course for so it's very important you
they certainly this twofold one is it's
good right from the start and second is
it will be really helpful for the future
um and part of the reason is in an ideal
world we shouldn't have to know our this
stuff things would just work the way
they're supposed to and you'd write
programs and you'd run them and who just
do what you want it to do and all that
stuff that maybe you should see in
science fiction movie but the reality is
of course things never quite work the
way they should and so if you really
want to fix things that are broken if
you want to make things sure the things
are secure you want to add some features
and our otherwise available you have to
understand more how things work and you
know computer science and in fact all
engineering is based on a set of
principled abstractions that we can for
example in physics you can understand
Newtonian mechanics and realize it's an
abstraction and it works a lot and you
can do a lot of stuff with it until
you're going really fast speed white and
all of a sudden it doesn't work so well
so you know that principle is is fairly
profound because science and engineering
that there's some layer of abstraction
that works 90% of the time and it's very
useful to thinking that terms of that
abstraction but the distractions don't
always hold and that happens over and
over again in computer science and
computer engineering and so part of this
is to sort of explore the boundaries
between the usual abstractions you get
as a programmer and what's going on more
of the hardware and the system software
level to be able to be a factor so let's
just give you some examples and the
saying I have hints are not integers you
know when you declare I'm very boy C
called you int and so for example I'm
learned in algebra that if you square a
number it should always be greater than
or equal to zero if it's either a real
number a rational number an integer um
so let's test this hypothesis and so I
actually wrote this really simple
program here OS Q dot C and what it does
is it has one function can you see that
well there oh that it just computes X
star X and we can run this you see it
takes it it reads values off the command
line arguments so I can run it on a
number like 40,000 and it returns 1 6
followed by a lot of zeros which is what
you'd expect but what if I run this on
50,000 so it should be 2 5 in a bunch of
zeros but no it's minus 170 949 6 7 2 9
6 so that doesn't look like the square
of any number with the 5 in a lot of
zeros it's negative it has no zeros and
something's funky so this is an example
of hints are not integers the reason of
course is that on this machine this is a
Linux machine that uses a 32-bit word
size so all numbers have to be
represented all the numbers that are in
are represented in 32 bits and the
square of 50,000 is too big to fit in
that representation so what happens is
it overflows and that causes it to
change the bit pattern very much so you
can imagine this could get you into
really big trouble if you are like
controlling a rocket and you want to go
at the square of 50,000 and it was
sending you somewhere negative and in
fact there's been examples of exactly
that happening with the Rockets going
bonkers because it was giving some bad
numeric values due to overflow so this
is an example of where the abstraction
is not working now you might if you're
used to Python you'd say wait a minute
I've done stuff like this all the time
and it works just fine it in fact you
can do some really big numbers and it
will halfway keep going because it uses
a way of representing numbers that they
just add as many bits as it needs to
represent that number so for better or
worse python gives sort of gives you
this more abstract wire that see that's
not about our numbers are represented
that lets it handle very large numbers
so again an understanding what languages
can do one is an important part of being
more effective at systems if I type
voting point numbers on the other hand
if I keep squaring a number it will
always be positive but actually that
turns out to be mildly interesting too
so another property you're used to with
numbers is the associative property of
rithmetic yeah you can for both addition
and multiplication you can move the
parentheses around and your final value
will be the same
and let's see I didn't write a program
for this but I can fire off the program
that you will get to know very well in
this course is called gdb it's called
the new debugger so it's used to help
it's a program that lets you've examined
operate and execute other programs and
see what's going on and it has built
into it a little interpreter so again I
can do my 40,000 trick and it will work
and if I change it to 50
it will give you that funky result
because it it's also mapping the than I
did
it's the 32-bit integers so I can use
this for a loading point as well again
again multiply some really big numbers
and it won't go negative on you but if
you go really big that's interesting so
a negative so anyways you can see not
only way you'd expect but what I really
want to show about floating point is I
can take numbers like 10 to the 20th
which is pretty big number and subtract
10 to the 20th and add some other number
and except for 3.14 being turned into
3.13 and a bunch of nines you see that I
got what you'd expect you take a big
number you and it's negative than 0 and
then add 0 to 3.14 and it's fine but if
I take I move those parentheses around
then I get zero and the reason for this
is if I am 3.14 to minus ten in the
twentieth think of scientific notation
where you only keep some number of
positions past a decimal point
gently xx kind of Dwarfs 3.14 and so
that some there on the right guy
computed is just minus 1 to the 20th or
10 to 20 and I add that to it 10 to the
20th million 0 so you can lose voting
point numbers can handle Hindle much
wider range but the trade-off they make
is they don't have the precision and so
you can lose significant things and
again if if you don't understand this
and you're trying to do numeric
computation you can get yourself in
trouble so we'll spend a fair bit of
time in this course learning about
numeric representations how what their
actual formats are and some of their
properties cuz it turns out that's a
certain cornerstone that you really need
to understand in a lot of parts of
computer science they some years ago
made this course of prereq for the
computer graphics course cuz they wanted
the students come in to understand
floating-point arithmetic so sometimes
you see these numbers and they look
completely random you know minus 1 1967
whatever that was but there's actually a
very predictable set of properties that
determine what numbers pop up when that
happens except for that one I just
showed you that I really don't know it's
just that it doesn't always match your
intuition about if you've had algebra
calculus as your background this isn't
what you'd expect because it doesn't
machen it has to do with this here the
finiteness of the representations uh but
on the other hand they do have certain
principles that you can know and
understand and those are important so
that's one of the first things and we'll
spend a fair bit of time in this course
just going over that both in lectures
and in oh man another big chunk of this
course is about
assembly language a machine level
programming so understanding the actual
low-level instructions that get executed
when you run a program and it's a little
bit there was a trend before this course
started that was getting away from
students every morning assembly code
basic in this era
there's no essentially no reason to
write significant amounts of code
directly in assembler assembly languages
just to let you know is a sort of
cleaned up
textual version of the low-level machine
code that gets executed and so there
really a very direct correspondence
between assembly code machine code and
all tend to go back and forth between
those two terms but the idea that we
found we found is that no you're not
actually we're not training you to write
code in this rather arcane notation but
we're training you to be able to look at
code that's been generated by say a C
compiler and understand what that
compiler did to transform your C code
into the machine code and what that
implies when that code then runs on the
machine either because it's running
slowly or it's got some quirky bug or
it's part of a security flaw that
attackers are trying to exploit some of
the weaknesses in your code and use it
to gain access to the system those are
all the kind of places where the actual
low-level machine code is fairly
important to understand so we'll spend a
fair amount of time covering that topic
as well and looking at programs from
sort of both directions high from high
to low and go to high another carp we'll
look at is a lot of times when you write
a program you know that it uses a lot of
memory but in a modern computer gives
you this abstraction that you can access
huge amounts of memory in it but the
reality is that
that's physically in your computer is
limited and it has some characteristics
that there's actually a hierarchy of
memories from some things that are
within the processor chip to parts of
their chips outside of it to even a disk
drive are all layers of this memory
hierarchy and the operating system and
the hardware all work together to kind
of make you think that you're accessing
a lot of memory but what it gives you is
very different performance
characteristics depending on what your
memory access patterns are and it can be
really somewhat bizarre until you
understand how it works and what the
underlying system does and this
attribute is becoming more and more
important over time that memory systems
are growing you can easily get a
computer with 32 or 64 gigabytes of
memory of RAM but the access speed of
those is much slower than the processing
rate of your actual processor so you see
more difference between the memory
performance in the processor performance
over time oh and there's also other
features especially in a language like C
or C++ about how you reference memory
that can lead to some really really
awful and nasty and painful bugs
so this is a very simple example of a
structure structure in in C that has a
an integer array called a with two
elements followed by a double D and this
function that will write some number to
an arbitrary position in that array a
and if this were in Java another
language it would only let you use a of
I would only allow you to reference
either a of 0 or a of 1 of course but in
C and other languages there is no bounds
checking and so it will go ahead
the reference a of 39 say and you'll be
effectively assigning you'll be storing
in memory someplace a number that has
absolutely nothing to do with what
normally should be stored there so if
you look at this function what it should
do you realize is essentially nothing
right then it set some value the the
double to 3.14 and vets value return so
it just should return 3.14 and it sets
some memory position but there's no
obvious way that setting what effect the
program behavior well let's just give it
a drop so I call that the program struck
tonight I can give that value of eyes
communal honor
so you'll see if I give it either as
your one for the value of I it returns
just like you'd expect 3.14 if I give it
the value two then things start to look
curious that it's not really 3.14
anymore so that looks pretty weird to
think about that pretty exciting yes you
got it
good good observation so we'll go into
that but you've got the idea that I've
basically I I've stood I've smacked a
little piece of that double and so it's
no more quite 3.14 and if I do that to
three then my 3.14 turns into two in a
fight go to four then I crash the system
because it detected that this is not a
valid access which is good actually
you'd rather have detect it then some
you'll see other places you'll have this
experience you maybe already have that
you can modify you know write to some
bad pointer it'll set something your
program will go merrily long it might
run for minutes hours days weeks and
then eventually it will come to a place
where as to reference a memory location
then it's screwed up and some awful bug
occurs but can you figure out where that
bugs got injected no way so that's one
of the more painful classes of bugs to
try and track down but at least with
this course you know why even if you
don't know where or how in the example I
show here gave slightly different
results on a different machine um so yes
the observation that was made is if you
look at the way memory is organized for
this struct I'm starting with the lowest
addresses at the bottom and each of
those rectangles represents four bytes
so the two ends of a are each four bytes
there so first day of zero and then and
one but then there's eight bytes to make
a double and the first eight of them are
the low precision low order bits of of d
and so when I zapped them I didn't you
know totally find the number I just kind
of knocked some of the lower decimal
points and then the upper part of it is
the sort of high level bits the more
higher precision bits of d and so when I
whacked that I really changed civilian
some span toys and then in this case
when I hit four it was hitting some kind
of critical state that could
that there is some corruption of memory
that occurred here and it gave a fall in
other times on different compilers as
can rotten werewolf happily let me do
some of those but not all so that's an
example again of if you understand more
of the sort of underlying how memory is
laid out how data structures have
weighed out what can occur then these
things are at least understandable even
if they're annoying embarrassing and
that's sort of a reality if you write in
C or C++ and so a lot of people choose
not to by writing in another language
which is fine I have nothing against
other languages but the reality of
course is a lot of this code in the
world is written in C or C++ and that's
just one of its features in these ways
you can try to avoid some of those
problems oh another part we'll look at
this course is sort of programmed
performance and we look at that at many
different levels
oh and so i I actually of course like
122 or other courses you've learned the
sort of Big O notation and the idea of
asymptotic complexity so one program is
quadratic
another is n log N and log ends a lot
better than quadratic so do that use
quicksort don't these bubbles work but
there's more to it than that you know a
lot of times if you're running a video
encoder and you want to have a frame
rate of 30 frames per second and you can
only get 15 frames per second then it's
not an asymptotic complexity problem
it's just go twice as fast and it will
make a big difference to you so there's
a lot of times in the engineering world
where you're also worried about constant
factors too and there's a lot of slack
in the system each way that you can
overcome if you understand enough about
program execution to be able to optimize
performance so we'll spend some time on
that too that's a useful outcome so one
thing that certain combines this idea
of the memory system and performance is
this these two functions that both
perform absolutely the exact same thing
their purpose is to copy the elements of
a source array to destination array
where both of those arrays are both size
2048 rows and 2048 columns and so you
see that the two programs are absolutely
the same except for the order of the of
do you do the copying row wise or column
wise right and the one in the the left
in the inner loop you see it's J which
is the second index so logically you're
going through the row kind of like this
each row one row at a time talking the
whole row and the other one I've flipped
it around so the inner loop is odd so
I'm sort of going through it column once
and stepping through it vertically but
note that the outcome is the same
they're the same thing it's just do I do
that row wise or column wise and if I
fire up a machine and run this though
you'll see that it makes up at 20 X 4 20
times difference in performance the row
eyes is much much faster than complex
and this is an example of this memory
hierarchy as mentioned earlier that
basically the row wise and we'll see
exactly why is more tuned to the way the
memory hierarchy sort of anticipates how
you're going to access memory patterns
and the column wise messes it up so if
you in fact if you look at the cover of
your book you'll see this picture and
it's an explanation of why row wise is
better than compromised so the upper one
that what this shows is for various
different access patterns how many
megabytes per second we can access the
memory yeah
is measured just by reading programs
like you saw here and seeing how fast
they go and you'll see that the first
one the row-wise is up in a pretty good
spot as far as throughput of over 8,000
megabytes per second and the one that
copy ji is at the worst possible place
it's here then down there in the below a
thousand megabytes per second so again
whoa whoa I understand this we call this
the memory Mountain for obvious ideas
the reason it was actually this way of
visualizing memory system performance
was developed by a fellow his graduate
student here at the time he was from
Switzerland so I guess this is his way
he liked to think about this Oh
so again this is one of these topics
that we cover in this course that really
can make a big difference in the
programs that you write and then another
part of this course we'll talk about is
beyond sort of writing the old programs
that Square numbers or access memory in
various ways there's a lot of
interesting other parts of the computer
system in particular the whole business
of hooking computers together and having
them talk to each other over networks
has many many layers of complexity to it
and various standards and protocols and
hardware and software and so forth that
we won't get deeply into you have to
take on networking or distributed system
of course you only do that but we'll at
least give you a sort of starting point
in that direction so that you'll better
appreciate what's happening with your
computer when you're using a wireless
access or when you're getting webpages
through a web browser so one thing about
this course it's different from the way
most systems courses are taught
including the more advanced ones that
you'll take after this is most systems
courses are kind of designed or built
around what how it takes to build a
system so if you're an an operating
systems course at CMU at least
and a lot of time writing the core code
of an operating system in the compiler
course you write a compiler the computer
architecture course you designed
microprocessors
so that's all really interesting
endeavor and it's really interesting to
do but we don't think it's the right way
to start when you first warning systems
the way we'd like to start our systems
is what we call a programmer centric so
how you as a programmer in this course
we mean a C programmer are how you write
code the exercises makes use and
interacts with different parts of the
system and how you can be more effective
and better at doing them so it gives us
an angle on it that lets you now after
this when you jump into an operating
system course and they teach you how to
write a signal handler you don't from
this course then wondered what a signal
handler is and what you some value has
in certain applications programs so
we're mostly looking at application code
here but it will give you a watching
point so that when you go into more
advanced systems programming system
design you'll understand what it is
you're trying to achieve
and that works out really well this user
perspective or programmers perspective
works out really well for an
introduction and also for satisfying
this goal we have a you should learn
something useful in this course even if
you never take another systems course
because the chance that you're actually
gonna go off to a company that designs
cache memories is pretty small there's
only a couple of ability and so you know
in the whole world the number of people
who design microprocessors who design
cache memories who implement operating
systems there's only a small fraction of
the total number of people who use this
stuff at various different levels of
sophistication and so we're sort of
preparing you after that broader task
yeah a life of programming in various
stores and a part of what we do is a lot
of this material that we cover is stuff
that in historically people just kind of
learned on the job or learn from their
friends or poked around or heard from
somebody else or run it on the internet
or something before there was an
Internet but but a lot of its what we've
tried to do is Conniff I it and put it
in one place so that even if you don't
have this sort of driving urge to dig up
everything and learn it on your own you
can learn it through us so as I
mentioned there's a lot of courses if
you look at that required this course as
a prerequisite and I know a lot of
people are in this course mostly because
they want to do other stuff and that's
fine but over time this course started
as a CS course but it's been adopted
into ECE and it's a core course in both
programs as well as people from the
number other programs on campus both
undergraduate and graduate who take this
course as a watching point for many
other courses and so one property of all
our advanced courses at CMU is they
expect you to know this material and
this part of the reason we have it so at
this point I want to turn over the
microphone to Brian who wants to talk
something about how he uses the teaching
of this course as a as a research
endeavor as well
that's more applause than it but I teach
it over the summer so I'm just need to
give a brief a two-minute quick spiel
which is that every semester we
basically do a little bit of educational
research so not only are we teaching you
all about computer systems we're trying
to understand better how well to teach
you computer systems so this is going to
entail those two particular things one
we're continuing to revise to change up
the recitations to as Randy is not yet
mentioned there will also be some sort
of in-class quiz now today and they're
not even really greeted so but these
things are both two things that we're
trying to do we're trying to update
we're just going to measure at the end
of the semester basically to see how
well you learn did you learn better than
the students last fall did it actually
help you learn did it help you use your
time better all these different kinds of
questions what do you need to do nothing
I mean you're just in the course you're
already learning in the course you don't
have to do anything particular to
participate if for some reason you don't
want your data included then you can
clean out myself or you can email Chad /
shocked who's that Everly Center and say
don't include my data now all your data
is going to be anonymized no one's going
to look at your ID no it's gonna look at
your past grades specifically we're just
gonna look at this and see some hash
code that says you know some long
sequence of letters and numbers scored
this well in the course and this quality
to the assignments and we'll look at
that and we're not even gonna look at it
until January so however you get on it
it doesn't matter it's not going to
impact your actual grade that Phil and
Ramey are going to assign you we're just
going to be doing the measurements and
look at it retroactively Lee and say did
it help did you learn better or not so
let's see you don't get any compensation
for doing this
sorry
yeah there's no actual interception I'm
telling you honestly exactly what we're
doing we're trying new things we want to
see that you actually learned if you
have further questions I'm always happy
to take emails I'm happy to meet with
you and discuss these things you know
this is one of my passions of not only
do I care about things like you know
actual computer systems but I care about
making sure that you're learning the
material and that we're doing that the
best and most efficient way possible so
that's it
the text is fully in the syllabus so
you're also welcome to read it there and
otherwise it's back to you Rainey
[Applause]
so if that seems a little weird to you
that we have to say now it's because
technically you are human subjects in a
research experiment and as human
subjects you have to be apprised of
what's going on and this research so is
very much oriented it's an educational
research so how to make courses at CMU
and elsewhere more effective so now I
want to jump into one of the less
pleasant parts of this course and that's
the issue of academic integrity so
academic integrity is sort of a broad
term that counts various forms of
cheating and plagiarism and I know
you've heard a lot about this in other
courses and some other places but it's
especially a problem in computer science
there's many tools and techniques that
make it very easy and very tempting to
acquire information in in ways that
you're not supposed to and it's been a
problem for this course and others that
we really take very seriously and part
of it is I we as instructors feel this
special obligation in this course that
if you are going from this course into
say the operating systems course we
wanted to make sure that you've really
mastered
Tyrael in a way that those people are
expected you've mastered it and if
you've done it by ill-gotten means
chances are you haven't growing rid of
the material and that's a problem so
it's not just that I'm a mean person and
vengeful on things it's like to us all
of us we feel like this is our one of
our real obligations as instructors and
also I should say one of the least
Pleasant parts of the job that I have so
in general then and you'll see in the
syllabus a fairly in-depth discussion of
what's allowed and what's not and I
really advise you to look very carefully
at that but in general all the
assignments you do the labs in this
course is eight of them are done on your
own and we may really on your own you
can make use of information that's in
the textbook on the class web pages you
can talk to the TAS or the instructors
but you really shouldn't be cooperating
with each other in any significant way
in getting your assignments done also
the reality is use a lot of stuff on the
web that makes it possible to bypass
some of what our goals for this course
are as from learning this textbook gets
used at 320 schools around the world and
some of the labs were developed and are
made available although we've tended to
tweak the lamps that you see here
they're not quite the same as the
textbook ones but as a result there's a
lot of little hidden places on the web
that have material that might be
relevant to some of your assignments and
so it can be easy tempting and sometimes
feel almost necessary to make use of
that information and we really aim to
make that not happen
so in general acquiring information from
others from the web in ways that isn't
appropriate is is not allowed and the
other part of it is it's the other side
of it is we also don't want you to
supply information
two students in this course in or in
future versions of this course and we
put on you an obligation now and forever
to not be disclosing information
relevant to the labs in this course for
other students and I can say this you
should realize it if you look at the
academic integrity policies of the
university one of the things they say
queer is there's no statute of
limitations its meaning even if you get
through this course and you're not
caught doing something and you get a
decent grade you're not really home free
we've we detect something in the past
that was unauthorized we can go back and
through a process of change your grade
and possibly revoke you to group so not
to sound too scary but it's true and
we've done there's a special problem
with github that a lot of students like
to use GIMP which is a great way to do
version control but github if there's
ways that your account if you you might
have it as a private currently but it
will become public after some period of
time and so you can endeavour Tinley
we've stuff lying around that really is
effectively disclosing information to
future students so what is not cheating
then and I use the term cheating
plagiarism interchangeably oh it's okay
to work with other students if they're
having trouble getting their code to
compile the debugger to work sort of
system level stuff that's fine very very
high level design issues and that's one
where people are often misinterpret what
we mean by high level design so if
you're here's an example of a case I had
several years ago oh we didn't we didn't
I didn't cheat I was reading my code
and my friend was typing it in or we
went on the whiteboard and worked it all
out in pseudocode and but then we all
did the coding our sauce that pseudocode
is code and even if it's pseudo the
point is if it's at that level of detail
where you have to be writing it down to
explain it to somebody that's not a high
level high level means just in general
oh I found it best to you know array
axises array row wise rather than column
wise in general there's a lot of code
available through the book web page the
course web pages and things and of
course you can use make use of them so
again as I mentioned that the syllabus
goes into fair motor detailing them so
what happens so I should mention that
we're pretty good tracking this stuff
down I'm probably better or as good at
using a web search as you are and so we
we find these things if you found a copy
of some code on github from some student
in Iowa we've probably already found
that code then make sure have copies of
it we also have copies of every single
submission made in this course over its
entire history and we run these programs
where there are called cheat checkers
that will just take we can literally
make this big pot of all the assignments
that ever have been created and then
throw in your code and it does this
analysis in comparison that doesn't get
fooled by things like changing comments
or variable names or indentation or
things like that and it comes back with
matches and some of the top matches are
false you just sort of happenstance but
others will look very fishy and
suspicious to us Mets when we start
looking more closely so it's actually
pretty hard to to trick the
programmers and once it happens we begin
a process where we several eyes will
look more closely at the code and if
it's suspicious then we'll call you in
for a meeting which can be a very
uncomfortable meeting and just as a
consequence our our minimum penalty is
always a minus hundred percent for that
assignment so it's always worse then if
you haven't turned into anything at all
but that's actually when we're when
things you know when there's some
extenuating circumstance or you're
honest about it there's other cases and
not uncommon in fact the default case is
that we give you a failing grade the
assignment that goes on your permanent
record and all of these are marked as a
ID by the university and the rule at the
university is one a IV okay hope you
learned your lesson - a IDs you get
count in front of a board consisting of
faculty and other students where you
have to explain it and they can assess
the penalty which can be that the
maximum penalty we as instructors can
impose is to fail of course but they can
impose expulsion and they do I've been
in several of the hearings for somebody
who is on their second instance and they
were expelled from users so just as for
example two years ago we had twenty
students we failed the course dude that
that's about 5% of the students in the
course one of them at least one of whom
subsequently is expelled from the
University last a couple of years ago I
I we came across some code that showed
up in a lot of people's implementation
to one of the labs track down where it
would come from and then went back
through several years of submissions and
found this same source in a lot of
people's assignments and so we went back
and through a process involved multiple
professors and the University Dean of
Student Affairs we actually penalized
we graded and assigned new grades to
eleven different students who had
already taken the course and some who
had already finished at CMU so we really
do take that no statute of limitations
here absolutely and what they I'll just
say personally is I don't like doing
this and I don't even like talking about
it I feel like there's a tremendous
waste of my time to be looking at
somebody's assignment trying to figure
out whether it's a copy of this other
one that's on github and it's spending
time talking to the students and hearing
they're you know they're kind of dodging
the issue until they finally fess up
confessing and state what they really
did and going through this whole process
it's very painful it's emotionally
actually very difficult for me and it's
way more difficult for the students so
and I know all of you here have no
intention of cheating in the course but
what happens is as that deadline draws
near and you're just not getting the
assignment done and you know there's a
copy line out there it's just so so it
happens and it's but the consequences
are really really terrible question moss
generates a lot of this question is good
one what about false positives a lot of
false positives and there's been a few
times when we'll have that meeting with
the student and there is some
explanation and nothing happens but you
have to realize that we as instructors
don't have to have your confession to be
able to apply consequences we can say I
believe you cheated I'm going to give
you this penalty you have the right to
appeal it and I think it's a good thing
to appeal if it really was unjust we try
not to do this but you know we don't
we're not the judge or the jury we don't
have to
have proof beyond reasonable doubt this
occurred we can say I believe that this
is what I believe you can appeal so I've
never had that happen to me that case
but I had some number of students where
they come in and there's some
explanation and that's okay so let's
just go through a few examples here you
know if you start using searches for 213
bomb lab which will come up actually
with some interest in YouTube videos I
know and I've looked at those videos
that I've watched so we kind of know
what's there but you shouldn't be doing
that right that's clearly a case where
you're trying to gain information to do
an assignment not the technical
information but something to help you do
a solution in general of course
supplying a code that's a fairly evident
thing giving a file that's pretty
evidence that as I mentioned also
writing sooner Lakota on a whiteboard is
also sharing of new information on the
other hand you know if you need
reference material about some library
functions that's for or particular
programs that's fine TAS we have a lot
of office hours it's always fine to talk
with that I'm gonna in the interest of
time skip this over but I recommend you
look at some of these scenarios that are
very typical of what I've experienced
that some students as I said the
deadline is approaching you have to get
this in it's not working if you find on
github a student from some of the places
written code that more or less works
make a copy of it try and fix it up some
submit it fine but then we find that we
can and
find those cases and then have these
meetings that I described to you um
here's some a little bit more scenarios
that so Ellis is working on a lab it's
not working
and Bob is sitting next to her he's done
that bob is the next to Charlie and
Charlie's not doing so well so Charlie
gets up for a break and Bob makes a
print out of his own code and reads
about Charlie's chair who is cheated
Charlie verb I swear to Bob I don't know
what he's doing you know it probably is
what its intention there was it just
because that was the nearest thing to
put it on or not but there's definitely
sketchy charlie obviously is oblivious
to this at this point but then Charlie
find us a copy looks it over and copies
one function and fixes it up so that one
Bob sits down with Alice and they go
over her code together what's the
problem Bob or Charlie both right
they're working together Charlie looks
at the screen that Bob left behind and
sees what's going on who cheated there
well Corinne Charlie did Bob price
shouldn't have left his screen
unattended but you know there's some
level of expectation you can have in
this world then it's an expectation of
privacy that you don't expect you have
to lock everything you do and put
passwords on it but in general that was
not good for Bob to just leave the
screens like oh I was having trouble GDD
how to set a breakpoint in it he shows
her
that's okay that's fine Joey goes to TA
for help that's fine so one thing we're
doing that just started last spring in
this course because a lot of students
were using github and it's their code
repository and in fact I'm a fan of gift
myself but the best thing about github
is the gift not the hub so git is a
general-purpose version control program
that as long as you can find a servers
that supports gift you can use it you
don't have to use the commercial one
called github and so ECE has a version
control runs a get server and we are
really gonna strongly push you to use
that instead of github and there's a
sort of a carrot and a stick involved
here so one is it's really a good habit
to use version control as you make
changes to programs you want to be able
to recover if you've made some change
and find out it was really a bad idea
you want to get back to some previous
state and can do that you can create
different branches you don't have to
worry about your computer crashing and
losing files and things like that you
can document your changes all those are
properties of gift
venez or any variant server but gets
especially good now the reason we wanted
to use this is this can actually also be
a record of your effort in this lab that
can be very important if we start asking
questions so if we this tablet I haven't
done this yet but both last spring in my
summer there are multiple instances
where students got called in because we
thought some of their code looked a
little fishy and some of the students
actually had a pretty significant record
of the work they'd done through get and
could show that this had consistently
been something you're working on and
therefore they were absolved of any
wrongdoing but other students all of a
sudden oh no I didn't save anything or
yeah I saved a bunch of stuff but then
all of a sudden it changed in this
massive way that looked like maybe some
blue code was important into it so you
can think of gap being your record that
we can look at we can look at the get
logs of your code on this ECE server for
this course as a record of it so we
really want you to make use of it both
through you don't benefit as a
programmer but also is is that suit of
record that can determine that this is
really your own doing your own code that
you've been working so a few logistics
three instructors for the undergraduate
we have lectures and recitations one
thing that we're going to introduce it
was started west of summer is canvas
which is the new blackboard in which I'm
generally not very familiar
I never use blackboard either but it has
its fit Sony where we can do with all in
class quizzes and these aren't by
quizzes like write down and paper and
passing Memphis's a few multiple-choice
questions and these actually are very
useful for the instructors is a way to
kind of gather a sense of where the
class is in their understanding and
dynamically and real-time modify what
we're presenting is a way to do that if
you ever been in a class with the
clickers have you done that I've never
used them but then it's the same general
idea it's just you'll use so you should
plan on bringing off a laptop or I guess
you can use your smartphone to do this
too so now we're not really grading them
but in the end on the grading if there's
sort of a borderline case on a student
where they're right at some the cutoff
for one letter grade versus another
if we see sort of an active
participation as like sorry I won't be
able to traffic who's in the class under
in your basis but you know
the the record we have for your
participation in these will be an
indication of how actively involved you
were in the class and that could affect
your grade so there's not a like numeric
value if you miss a class don't worry
about it we have them on weck we have
them on video there's a lot of material
on the web we're not taking attendance
in any formal way but your participation
could be beneficial to your grade
besides the fact we were in the material
better of course - okay so the book get
the third edition don't give anything
else don't get the International Edition
they really screwed it up the Chinese
version is okay we know the translator
really well but and then we also
strongly recommend you get this the C
book written by Kernighan and Ritchie
Ritchie was one of the originators of
the C language at Bell Labs both the
word go - one time this book is really
old and really a little bit out of date
because he has evolved over times but
it's still the best book because it's
not only the language itself but it
gives you some really nice little
programming examples that sort of show
style and how to think about programs
and things that is better than any of
the other books we've seen um this
course is going to have eight labs if
you know anyone who's taken it before
they've had seven labs and I'll tell you
about that and the lamps are really the
main thing you'll do for this course and
the main way you'll learn in this course
and you probably heard that for your
friends always there's two exams they're
both done using an online exam system so
we're not scheduled for the real
with no paper tests at all so there's a
lot of resources the class web pages has
a lot of stuff on it we use a Piazza is
their way of having questions from the
students and make also making a lot of
announcements will be there too so
that's the way you should definitely be
on Piazza poll here by default any post
you make will be private to the
instructors and we recommend you keep it
that way if there's some question that
recurs and it seems like it's worthwhile
for the whole class to know then we
might turn your private post into a
public one an appropriate way of course
just as a way to present that
information to a class but in general
it's more of a private way that you can
reach either us or any of the 20
teaching assistants of course I don't on
the other hand post code there not
because we don't like code but it's just
not the right way to do it
we have Auto lab which is the way we
submit assignments so if you ever need
help with code what you should do is
submit it to auto web and then tell us
about it and then we can go to auto 11
and get hold of your code and look at it
instead of us dealing with big files yes
the question was what wouldn't
submitting to Ottawa account is a
submerge submission for all of our
assignments you're allowed to submit as
many times as you like these no
penalties whatsoever for every one of
our assignments so email we don't have a
class email list but you can contact any
of the instructors or individual
teaching assistants we have office hours
every day of the week except for
Saturday from 5:30 to 7:30 in the wean
hall clusters and that's but they're not
going to start until next week there's
walk-in tutoring that exists and we
won't put information that online once
we have it and you can always schedule
office hours all three of us have
regular office hours or you can schedule
time there's fairly extensive
information in the syllabus about a
procedure if you feel like you've been
graded unjustly in either an exam or a
assignment there's a process for doing
that that has a time limit of typically
a week or so so we definitely understand
that where we make mistakes in grading
and we're very willing to hear requests
for great changes but don't expect at
the end of the term to come back with oh
i'm the lab 1 and lab 3 and the midterm
I was granted long it's too late by that
so look at the syllabus question how the
assignments work is it similar to 122 or
there's some aspect of it that's like an
auto grader you can see or is it all
just so the question was is this like
122 we actually talked one if 22 how to
do automated so
I'm the dick fan auto-graded I used to
say I would rather spend three hours
writing Auto graders that one hour
grating tape itself we ought oh great
like crazy so in fact for everything you
do you will know almost your entire
score Auto graded and then there's some
small part that we do manually like
style points and some of that but we
like are the auto grading kings of the
world so in general this is actually a
personal belief of mine and of all of us
that you'd benefit a lot more from the
quick feedback you get that the
absolutely wrong they have the chance to
fix it rather than submitting something
it's buggy and then two weeks later
you're told
oh there's a bug in your code too bad so
I think there's much more learning value
of of giving that quick feedback so it's
not just that we're lazy so you can just
submit you can submit something yes
question yeah yeah yeah yeah early and
often that's a great thing about
computers so we have some special
machines that are reserved for this
course called the shark machines most of
the work you do in this course you could
do on essentially any Linux machine and
even some non Linux machines but the
grading auto lab is actually run on a
set of Linux servers maintained by
competing facilities go we have these
very specific machines to shark machines
that where we kind of make sure the
software is configured and designed to
run properly on that so when in doubt
use those machines for doing your work
question
this is an interesting question and I'll
give the short answer which is make sure
whatever you submit it last is the thing
you want graded because that's the only
thing we actually put okay okay I think
quite easy good question um so just a
few other policy things we do have grace
days as a way for you to certain deal
with your schedule there's deadlines for
every assignment over the course of the
term you allowed to keep my weight of
total of five weight days we call those
grace days some assignments allow up to
two so none someone it's all in the
schedule and that's what we want you to
use if your ear press because you have
multiple classes you're going off on a
job interview
you have to go home for the weekend for
your grandmother's birthday any of that
stuff is you know that's purpose grace
days so that we're not having to deal in
a class of this size with every special
case of of can you give me an extension
through this with that we also well if
you don't if once you've used up your
grace days and those are assigned
automatically you have no control over
you know which assignments you're using
grace days or not on as soon as their
weight you start eating into those we
give also often up to three days like
total for assignments where there's a
sort of just an increasing thickness
penalty to it um and so we expect that
will take care of almost all the cases
people might not be able to get things
in time if there's something really
serious it goes
your life and this happens in one form
or another those are generally
significantly not just for this course
but your whole participation in all your
courses and so that's the time when you
need to go talk to your course advisor
and the adviser can get in contact with
us and basically work out a plan for how
to get back on schedule one of the
things that's difficult about this
course or pretty much any courses we get
this there's a lot of momentum rolling
in this and once you start falling
behind it's really hard to then get
caught up again you get loaded down and
you get further behind in things so my
main advice is hey don't use the grace
days till you really need them to try
and save them up toward the last few
assignments in the course which are the
ones that are the most significant and
also you just never know what might came
along that will prevent you from getting
things done on time so try to you know
be prompt keep on top of things
throughout the course generally it's
fine to have laptops here but we don't
like other things and we want you doing
productive work and that not Facebook
the course grade is half exam and half
labs the labs have different point
values you can see on the assignments
page the point distribution for the
different assignments we tend to grade
just on the point or standard grading
scale with no we don't curve the course
we often work out quite a few A's and
quite a few B's in this course and
that's fine if we feel you've shown
mastery in the material we have no
problem giving you a good grade as I
mentioned we sometimes will bump people
in a positive direction if they're right
on the border there's some circumstance
that seems to argue in favor of one
thing I want to mention is there's a new
lab that's available today you can get
it from the course page if you should
all have all the way of accounts already
if you are registered for this course by
noon yesterday but in general there's a
new lab out called web zero which is a
little exercise and C programming which
if you've done any C programming if
you've taken 122 should be a very
straightforward exercise we hope that's
the case but what we found is some
number of students coming into the
course they're either weakened it
they're a little rusty some reason
haven't done much C programming and they
find they get stuck and the problem is
if the problem occurs not in the first
few laps but in later on in the course
about a month in when you have to start
writing more significant programs so lab
0 is our our new attempt to sort of help
give you some assessment it only counts
two points total in your grade but it
also should only take you one hour or so
to do so but you can get on to that
right away it's due a week from Thursday
otherwise the labs are once we hand in
this course for some time
although we keep tweaking and improving
them in various differences just so the
lamps are really a big part of this
course and I'm sure if you talk to
people taking the course before that's
what they remember the most it's a great
way to learn material is to actually get
your hands on a duplex well we use a
system called the project zone for
passing out the handouts the write-ups
for the labs and it's so a way that
actually kind of reveals the handout
slowly over time as you answer your
questions on what you've already seen
and only when you get to the very end
you get this little passkey which is a
set of digits than the letters but then
you include as part of your submission
and that's what lets you submit things
to all the way out and the reason we do
this is often we get questions in Piazza
where our answer is read the handout and
so this is a way to encourage you more
strongly to read the handout carefully
before you jump into the sciences and as
I mentioned we'll have a gift server the
last thing I want to talk about is
there'll be a bootcamp this Monday which
I know is Labor Day at 7 p.m. in ration
auditorium but the TAS will run on
getting familiar with Linux and gift so
a lot of you this isn't mandatory at all
but if you consider the little shaky on
using Linux using command-line tools
using get they'll cover a lot of that
and so I recommend you you put that on
your schedule otherwise I think we're
good to go so what do I do with you