[Applause]
greetings everyone
so last time to sort of the introduction
to the course overview and some of the
logistics today we'll get into the real
content in general I'm not going to
spend a lot of time in this course
making announcements and things but for
the first two I want to just make sure
people are queer so as you know this
coming Monday is Labor Day and so
there's no classes so therefore you
won't have recitation sections but we
are scheduling what we call a Linux boot
camp on Monday evening at 7:00 p.m. this
is completely optional if you have
experience in linux or you know command
line activities soon as soon Erik how do
you get code to run how do you edit
files while you move files around will
be covered will also cover some odd gift
because we're encouraging you to use git
server that's operated by ECE and by the
way people are various ways communique
us having trouble with that and the
honest truth is it's not all set up yet
my understanding is the person in ECE
who runs that is a earning man and he
goes there every year and they have this
same trouble every year so oh wait he'll
have a really great time there come back
well-rested fix things up you'll be
ready to go hopefully by the time of
this boot camp Oh like I said this is a
won't do over the courses term a few of
these evening sessions review sessions
none of these are mandatory at all
they're here to help you we may or may
not record them in video we will in all
cases post whatever materials were
passed out or used like your slides or
code examples or something like that
will be made available on our website
also to mention as I mentioned last time
there is a new lab for this course
called lab zero it's intended to be
a walkthrough of basic C programming
that hopefully you already are fairly
comfortable with and so it really should
make take much time one to two hours
potentially to do it and we encourage
you this will be due a week from today
at midnight we encourage you to get
going on that right away you don't need
an auto web account you don't need a
gift of account you don't need much of
anything except access to the files
which are on the website and to some
type of machine that you can compile an
execution code I've tested it on my Mac
and on Linux I don't think it would work
correctly and windows because it makes
uses some Linux libraries but if you
know if you have a Windows machine and
you want to set it up there's a open
source software called cig win cy g wi n
that you can create a certain unix-like
environment on it on a Windows machine
and this is one we have this elaborate
system of wait days and grace days and
so forth none of that applies for this
first assignment either get it done or
you don't it's intended to be more of a
assessment for you to understand whether
you've got the sort of programming
background that we sort of minimum about
programming background we expect for
this course the other is those you who
are officially in the course yet are
perhaps on some waitlist please don't
contact us the instructors about
waitlist issues because it's not I
didn't even know how waitress work when
working with course administrators both
in the CS it needs to e to deal with
these and they are much better equipped
to deal with it earlier okay that said
let's move on in and this bet this
material we're gonna do in three
lectures cover all chapter two of the
book which if you open up your book and
you count pages you're gonna see a lot
of pages there so it's a pretty fast
move and these lectures will not
[Music]
and duplicate completely cover every bit
of material there it's the kind of thing
none of this is super advanced math but
you have to get really comfortable with
this is very foundational material you
have to be very comfortable with to move
on to other parts of the course so
you've grown up in an era where bits are
a sort of a fact of life it's
interesting that the term bit was only
actually first developed in in 1948 or
so by a phone and Claude Shannon we
didn't invent the bit but he invented
information theory which defined this or
the most primitive piece of information
as a difference and of course you know
that that everything in your computer is
is sort of organized and expressed in
terms of ones and zeroes and that I
don't know if you've ever sat back and
thought well I wonder why they do it
that way and the answer is well there
aren't reasons but it's not the only way
to do it for example that first a
computer sort of large-scale computer
was this machine called ENIAC and these
vacuum tubes to implement it was very
large heavy expensive machine and they
encoded everything in decimal using one
vacuum tube with basically ten vacuum
tubes for every digit that would be on
if you think of him as on or off it
would represent which of values zero
through nine is one of those vacuum
tubes in the air so it wasn't always the
case that powers of two were sort of the
dominant way of thinking about even
computers but nowadays you did too close
and there's a few good reasons from a
sort of systems design perspective one
of them is that in terms of electronics
if you actually hook up an oscilloscope
or some other meter to electric the
signals
going in and out of your chips or
somewhere you'll see that they're not
these perfect smooth square wines they
have bounces variant and simile the
devices that we build circuits out of as
you know are extremely small and not
that well engineered as far as nice
Queen responses and things and so the
advantage of doing everything in powers
of two is her bits is that you can deal
with a lot of noise or uncertainty or
imperfection in the system and still
reliably extract from it a signal of
either 0 or 1
and especially for storing information
we won't go into too much in this course
but you can imagine there's some
circuits that have feedback loops where
you can either be feeding back a one or
feeding back a zero and that's a very
stable value whereas if you try to
discreetly represent more values than
that then you know decay or noise or
various other sources can drop the
signal so it's become sort of a matter
of course that everything we do is in
terms of one Suzy Rose and um and it's
important to understand that there's
nothing in a bit or a bit representation
that tells you for example this is a
number or this is a string or this is a
floating-point number or this is a piece
of code the bits are just a bit obvious
value 0 or 1 it's what we how we assign
meaning to those bits that determines
how we interpret them and that's sort of
a general abstract statement that will
keep coming back to it multiple points
in this course to make sure and really
reinforce that idea so so for example we
could represent a number like fifteen
thousand two hundred thirteen as a
string of ones and zeros and use a base
two representation and we can think of
numbers that are decimal numbers but we
can represent it
down in base two and in this case we'll
talk about this a week from today we
know I'm going to call it the decimal
point though we call it the binary point
where the mark a ssin is between a
values that have a weight of some
positive power up to like one two four
eight and once it have a negative power
of 2 which weighed like 1/2 1/4 1/8 and
so forth and so actually when we
represent floating point numbers we're
using a base 2 representation so the
floating point number one five two and
three point zero is represented as a
binary number but with a binary point
and then weighted by the two to the 13th
which is what what it takes has nothing
to do with 15 two and three it has to do
with what it takes to get a number that
somewhere between 1 and 2 scaled up to
be 15,000 so again these are fairly
straightforward ideas but you just have
to keep coming back to this all the time
if I see a bit string I can't know in
advance what whether it's one number or
another or what its representation is
and I can interpret in different ways so
there's various ways that you can
represent small or bit strings you can
write it all off minor it but that gets
to be kind of cumbersome when you have
say a 64-bit value to write out the
string of ones and zeroes and so what
we'll typically do in this course and
it's fairly commonplace is to pack them
sort of group them into four bits at a
time so that some value between 0 and 15
if you think of it numerically and we'll
represent that as a single digit in
hexadecimal notation hexadecimal meaning
power 16 representations and rather than
suffixing numbers with what base were
used
we'll do it the way it's written and see
which is to say that we'll just prefix
something with zero X could be an upper
lower case X the letters in there can be
lower upper case it doesn't matter but
basically we will use the digits 0
through 9 of course a through F which
encode these 16 possibilities and so one
of the things skills you will acquire in
this class whether you want it or not is
the ability to fairly easily go between
a bit pattern and one of these 16
characters which sounds like a strange
skill to acquire but it's actually quite
useful so for example the way we
represent the instead of writing out 15
to 13 in binary we would group that by
saying well 0 1 1 is 3 on this table and
1 0 1 1 is d 0 1 1 is 0 6 & 1 1 0 1 is
I'm sorry D and then dude
by the way my trick on this is I
memorized 0 0 through 9 is pretty
straightforward I know this is a I know
this is C and I know this is 1/2 and I
kind of interpret the other ones between
at this when I don't have the table if
you have to if you're stepping on a
desert island having to encode thank you
tax this
interesting quandary HP it writes Oh
and so one of the things will keep
coming back to this when we looking at
typical values on the machine there is
no standard there's no uniform standard
and so people will talk about well
what's the word size of your machine and
is it a 32-bit machine or a 64-bit
machine you'll hear all those terms
thrown around and the truth is none of
those are very meaningful in particular
like this Windows machine or my standard
basically Intel microprocessor is
actually the hardware and there is built
to support 64-bit operations integer
operations addresses and so forth but it
can also run in a a compatibility mode
that goes back to actually the long the
early 90s where the machine only
supported 32-bit operations and so we'll
talk about a 64-bit machine and a 32-bit
machine but the truth is that this one
machine is both and that's true probably
for most of the machines of any sort
that you'll encounter these days and so
it's really a combination of operating
system the compiler what code it
generates and hardware itself that
determines what the Machine type is and
that's so you can actually configure
when you compile code you will go into
this whether to generate 64-bit code or
32-bit code and most the machines you'll
feel so and you'll see that the basic C
data types for most parts are
independent of whether it's 64 or 32
bits except for when you quit let say
something is a long go see all of a
sudden it flips from four to eight
between and in which execution model
details and similarly the fighter is and
this is
Joey counts how four bytes is a standard
address on a 32-bit machine it's enough
to give you a range of about four
gigabytes of memory which when that came
along that was a lot of memories but
nowadays of course a lot of machines
have more than 40 gigabytes of RAM in
them and so that's part of the reason
why things have really shifted over to
64-bit
where now the range is far greater again
we'll keep coming back to this so down
at the lowest bubble then as I said
we're operating on bits and the same guy
who invented informations here at Claude
Shannon did a master's thesis in 1939
that or 38 or so that was like
considered the greatest master's thesis
ever because he linked up the idea of a
boolean algebra which was had been
developed by this magician from in
England in the late 19th century named
George Boole with how do you design
digital circuits and so the idea of bool
was trying to codify what we call
propositional logic reasoning about to
in vaults things Oh as an algebraic form
sort of making it more like math than
like something that sort of an abstract
philosophical concept and so his idea is
think of zero is like false and one like
true and now we can algebraically
introduce an operator like and that
gives you a true value only if both
inputs are true so a and B means both a
and B have to be true and similarly or
well either A or B has to be true on so
if both of our faults are 0 and then you
get a 0 and same with a negation you
just flip true and false and there's one
called exclusive or that we distinguish
between in
if an exclusive we say exclusive lore
means one or the other is true but not
both it's interesting in English we kind
of in fun way you can blur that
distinction between inclusive and
exclusive I can say would you like me to
cut off your left hand or your right
hand right and there's sort of an
implicit understanding that I'm not
gonna cut off both so if you think about
how we use or in ordinary discourse
sometimes they mean inclusive and
sometimes to be next but we'll
distinguish those obviously a student
operation so back when Shannon did this
actually it was back when instead of
transistors they had relays
electromechanical realized and they
built these remarkably complex systems
like whole telephone switching networks
out of these electromechanical relays
and he was the first to kind of come up
with basic principles that you can take
this Network realize and systematically
derive an expression describing when
you're going to get a connection from
point A to point B through this series
of real ones
makes you wonder how did they do this
before he thought of this so it's one of
those interesting things that after the
the linkage had been made it was so
self-evident that we can't imagine any
other way of doing things
oh so we can generalize them from just
as simple zero or one true/false value
to basically a whole string of bits or
what we call a bit vector and if you
think about it learned on a computer we
have 32 or 64 bits we can think of those
as not just representing a number but
just as string of zeros and ones and
when we can apply these same operations
to strings of bits so we say and they
apply now on a bit for dense basis so if
we have an ant
we have to have a one in both both
elements in the column in order to get a
one as a result and similarly for other
operations and so you can see again more
you have to have one or the other and
the same kind of reasoning principle
says that the sort of simple zero in one
case applies to mostly holds for the
string of six case two now that one of
the actual very practical uses of this
is for thinking about set so imagine
that you have a maximum of 32 things and
so you want to represent different sets
or subsets of those 32 different things
well you can just use a bit string of
length 32 and say it's a one of a given
element is there a zero if it's gone and
then use now when you think of an that
becomes like intersection of two sets or
becomes like Union and exclusive are
becomes what they call a symmetric
difference between the sets so this is
actually used a lot in real life in
computers and you'll come across this
that will want to keep track of how many
different network connections are we
maintaining at any given time and be
able to selectively say I will accept an
incoming message from any of this subset
of the possible connections so there is
a actually a library that lets you
create these sets and manipulate them
but underlying it all all they're doing
is using these words of bits one or
multiple words to indicate them and so
it's sometimes this is sometimes called
a mask when you have a string of ones
and zeros the ones are the
that you're kind of interested in right
now and the zeroes are the ones that
you're you're not interested in and you
use an and operation than to just only
look at the items of interest so this is
sort of a very practical thing but it's
also very important from a mathematical
sense
and there's actually a theorem called
the stone representation theorem due to
a mr. stone but said there's a sort of
one-to-one mapping between an arbitrary
set as accountable and they basically a
big vector representation of that set so
in C and in actually most contemporary
programming languages you can actually
make use of those operations and well
you're gonna get some serious heavy-duty
experience with this in lab one which
will be out next Tuesday by the way of
learning how to love or hate or at least
make use of these bitwise boolean
operations and so the symbols that were
used earlier for and or an exclusive or
exactly the ones that C uses for these
bit-level operations until therefore
enough as well oh so for example we can
um look at some one byte value so one
byte values can record be represented by
two x digits and we can look at well
what would these operations be and
unless here like a row hex wizard you
probably can't just do that straight
away like what the complement of four is
oh but you could use the table and cheat
but what you can really do is right now
you know there is a binary expansion of
four and one
then you invert those bits and then you
go one zero one one and you'll find that
at the table of B and similarly one one
one zero is an e so pecs is is sort of a
convenient way to write things out but
not a very convenient way to reason
about things your question well it's a
care of data type so remember all
computers nowadays can represent various
different sizes so the underlying data
type care CH AR sometimes called char is
8 bits so yes you do have an 8-bit
computer I can you have many of them in
your lives but they also often are 16
32-bit and 64-bit computers - question
yes same thing if you think about that
subtraction of if you take all one's 15
and subtract that you don't have any
carries or virus so it will be exactly
the complement that's a useful way to
think about bit level operations
and simile I can say the compliment of
all zeroes is F actually I could do that
one in my head pretty easily and other
ones again you can drop down to a bit
level representation mapa didn't the
result you're looking for into bits and
then convert back to hex this class
isn't really going to be about like some
people can actually do addition and
multiplication and base 16 in their head
I can't do that and I figure if
computers can do it
why snuggler now one thing that's a
common got you and see both because
people don't know the difference or they
do and they forget or they make stupid
mistakes I do all the time is that the
other there's some other operations like
another kind of and that another kind of
or another kind of not and see and
they're really really really different
from the single ampersand version so in
this logic which is a different logic
there's only two values something is
either false or it's true
false is only wait to represent is the
value 0 but anything that's nonzero is
considered true in this context and so
when I say something is and if they're
both non 0 then they're both true and
I'll generate the value true but the
value I generate will always be 1 so
this is actually a useful we do it all
the time but keep in mind underneath it
it's kind of a funky way to think about
things so if we negate the value for 1
we get 0 because for one is and if by
the way don't make the mistake of
calling 41 because it's not it's for one
because it's basic - anyways Oh
41 is nonzero and so its complement is
false in this logic it's a different
thing in between 0 and on the other hand
it's companies
not negation this census disabil you
want and so in fact one of the tricks
you'll use in your first way up is if
you do two knots by the way I always
just say bang here bang bang we value
it's a waiting to convert it if it's
zero it will stay zero because it's
anything non zero will convert it one
the other thing that's important about
these operations both end in the bore is
that they are they have a certain early
termination trick and so you can say for
example this bottom one says if I have a
pointer called T I can safely say P
ampersand ampersand start it and what
will happen is look what will this
return if P is a null pointer zero and
what it will know it's that result is
going to be zero because zero and
anything is zero so it won't actually
evaluate the star P and that's good
because if he were a null pointer that
is dark he would give you an error so
you'll think about a few and you
probably know this already that if you
have a long sequence and use ampersand
to four vertical bars to to note it will
only evaluate as much the expression
enhanced you from left to right in order
to determine whether it's true or false
anyways you've probably heard this
before but if I make this mistake even
now not because I don't know the
difference but because I'm not very good
tightness so another class of operations
that you probably haven't spent a lot of
time using yet less here Joe experiences
shift operations and you can say shift
something left or shifted right but the
curious thing is certain to different
standard conventions for
that will make a lot of sense later
today or first thing in the lecture next
time but they don't make any sense at
all in total but I'll go over the rules
anyhow so in general what happens when
you shift something left is you just
slide the bits over that many positions
and you fill the the right hand side in
with zeros and whatever if there were
you know basically shift off the end
whatever was in the first three
positions on the left before that will
just disappear into nowhere shifting
right there's sort of two different
conventions the one that sort of the
natural one is what's called a logical
shift meaning I do the same IV I shift
some bits over I discard the ones that
are no longer needed and I fill it in
with zeros but there's another kind of
shift called an arithmetic shift and
what it does is it replicates the
leftmost bit of the the operand argument
and that's why in this example it's
shown and so as long as it's zero there
then arithmetic and logical shift will
be the same but if this example shows in
this second case where there's a a one
in that most significant point now when
I do a arithmetic shift I will fill in
with once which is not at all intuitive
that's a useful or a good idea but it
turns out when these are representing
potentially negative values this will
we'll get into later that's actually a
very useful operation think of a way to
divide something by a power of two
roughly speaking so what we'll see in
just a little while a while why do you
distinction now what are they and as you
know and see you can represent those
with double left double less than your
double in whether a whether a given
expression will evaluate using a
arithmetic or logical shift is a little
bit of tricky we'll talk about it later
there's only one way to do it the other
thing that's just general warning is
there's no it's sort of strict
interpretation and see of what it would
mean to shift something by a negative
number like you might think that
shifting left by minus one should be the
same as shifting right by the plus one
but there's no thanks
unlike you your machine will do that
simply if you say shift in number left
by 32 or by say 100 you'd expect maybe
you should get all zeros but that may or
may not happen and see as a language
makes no particular statement about
motion and that's by the way one thing
we're gonna see with C as a language is
that there's huge parts of it that are
undefined
meaning that basically the compiler
writer can choose how something that is
implemented and it may not do the same
thing from one machine to another to
another and that's a kind of a
disturbing feature when you try to write
programs that are designed to run across
multiple machines and compilers that was
one of the design goals of Java in fact
was to make sure that everything was
defined so that programs would be
completely portable but we're not using
Java in this course so we're gonna be
stuck with C and its quirks so
now just rolling along there's two main
classes and numbers we're going to
integer numbers we're going to want to
make use of in this course and one is
unsigned numbers meaning values that are
between 0 0 or positive and so we'll
call those unsigned because they they
don't need a sign to say whether it's
negative or public and then another
question number is if we refer to as
assigned numbers and there's many
different ways you could imagine
representing numbers that may be
negative or positive but the most common
by far and the way wool mostly
considered is what's called a two's
complement representation and the idea
of that is if you look at it from bit
representation the nonce ID number is
just a familiar binary representation
that you have a series of bits each is
weighted by a power of two ah the tweets
complement it's the same idea except the
most significant death has a negative
value associated with it and so we'll
show some specific examples of it so
let's look at two so complement is the
less intuitive one so the number 10 for
example is just positive number so the
first bit the sign bit will be 0 and you
see that the waiting of those values is
according to formula showed you before
that everything but the leftmost bit has
a positive weight in the left fifth one
has a
a negative value negative power of two
valuation and the other thing you'll
notice is that negative value is it's
more negative you know it's a it's a
heavyweight but say it's magnitude is
large it's two to the W the word size
here is 5 so 2 to the W minus 1 5 minus
1 is 4 minus 2 to the fourth is X so
we'd represent negative 10 then by
saying when you start with minus 16 and
what sets it is a little bit more
negative than a lot so I'll add that
form 2 to that in order to get it to be
minus town and that's the general scheme
of things that we a negative number we
start by making it very negative and
then we add back positive powers of 2 to
bring it back toward zero up to the
value oh and so for example this table
shows if you want to represent 15 to 13
or negative 15 to 13 16-bit numbers then
what you rely on is the fact that you
can set this most significant bit to
either 1 or 0 and it has a weight in
this case of two to the fifteenth or or
thirty two thousand seven six to it so
just using that very simple set of ideas
we can actually explore a lot about what
numbers can be represented and what the
representations will cross so for
example let's look at the unsigned case
the smallest number we can represent it
is obviously zero because we can't
represent any negative numbers but the
largest one we can get is if we pile in
all the ones we can into that
so you already saw it with a 4-bit
number it's f-111 one has value 15 which
is 2 to the 4th minus 1 not to the 4
minus 1 2 to the 4th minus and so in
general a bunch of ones will be
something that's apart almost a power of
2 but not quite similarly we can think
about two's complement numbers we can
have just that negative bit be our only
value that's the most negative value you
can possibly have and the most positive
values if we turn off that negative bit
and pile in all the positive parts of 2
we can and it will be in this case 2 to
the W minus 1 minus 1 and we can also if
we turn on the negative bit and all the
positive bits won't end up with minus 1
so 2 almost canceled each other out but
not quite and in general if you're
seeing a hex number it's a number it
goes ffff wah-wah-wah-wah
most likely what it is is the negative
number you know you're looking at the
whole string of ones that are sort of
the next very negative value a bunch of
ones to sort of bring it closer to zero
and then it's whatever it's left over so
for example to be more concrete if we
have 16 bits then its largest value of
the decimal number is 2 to the 16th
minus 1 so unsigned number or is a sign
number it's 2 to the 15 bytes work and
some weight a negative number so it's a
0 qualified which ones minus 1 is always
a bunch of ones and zeros always a bunch
of zeros so one of the curious
properties of this
as you'll see that there's a symmetry in
the representation that I can represent
a bigger an absolute value number as a
negative value then I can as a positive
value so anyway one figure out why there
is sort of a missing positive number in
there yes yeah we need space for zero
good so anything with a 1 in its first
digit first bit it's going to be a
negative number
anything with the zero on its first bit
will be either all zeros value 0 or ' so
that's why there's this asymmetry and
it's one of those things it doesn't
really matter most of time but when it
does it's really an annoying ok Oh
interest I mentioned done on pretty much
any computer you encounter nowadays you
can have sort of words you can operate
on values that are either 8 bits or a
byte 16 bits 32 bits or 64 bits are all
supported as data types in the language
up and you can see now that if X 32 is I
mentioned before 2 to the 32 is around 4
billion by the way
10:24 it's about the same mystical
sounds like the kind of stupid thing but
when I see it number 2 to the 32nd and I
one year when you're how big that is
well I see that it's 2 to the 30th which
is the same as around 10 of the night
plus 2 more that's a 4 and so it's
around 4 billion of course not exactly
as you can see but if somebody sort of
wants to throw around numbers and you
want to get some order of magnitude
sensitive this is actually fairly easy
so some people say that Microsoft switch
to 64-bit machines because they couldn't
represent Bill Gates is net worth as a
32-bit good news is we've got a long
ways to go
we 64-bit numbers before so in general
as I mentioned there's a sort of
asymmetry at the range and of course you
also notice that on the unsigned side we
can represent the number of this because
we can use all the bits in the positive
sense we can get roughly twice the value
others so if you're being careful in C
or any language for that matter you
should not you know be too casual about
assuming this range of numbers that
numbers there's never a guarantee that
all machines out there these night ever
wanted program use this two's complement
representation so these built in to see
there's a special include library file
called limit h that define the maximum
minimum values of a certain standard
numeric other standard data types and
those should be correct for the
particular machine or compiler that
you're working that said a lot of people
cheat and
assume that it has these certain
particular values okay so one of the
more curious ideas that we'll look at
and we'll explore in various ways is
what simulation then probably if we look
at a given bit pattern like what's shown
on the left and in some cases we might
think that is up unsigned number and
others is a two's complement number how
do those two numbers relate to each
other and what property we'll see as
it's shown in green here is if they're
nonzero numbers then they have the same
effect whether it's an unsigned there
are two compliment representation but
you'll see there's a sort of curious
mapping between the unsigned numbers as
they get bigger when they have a one in
their white position and and the
corresponding two's complement number
that they're actually there's a delta
there of exactly sixteen and so there's
some kind of curious properties of that
mapping that we'll talk about
but now as part of our experiment in
making progress in education I'd like to
try this
and we'll see I know you're gonna groan
and we might all go so if you go to the
course webpage and this is all right
I'll be amazed if this works but there's
a link on the left to canvas which as
you know is is the new version of
blackboard and you've probably used it
more than either because I never used
blackboard but if you go to that page
for this course which
are you finding some little problems
involved with all there should be three
problems each involving some things
there should be some way I can
oh this is more of an experiment I don't
think you'll be able to do you have to
be enrolled in the course you if you're
not enroll in the course just sit and
relax look over the shoulder of somebody
it's not cheating if you do
so the good news is I think this is you
guys here right and the quiz answer is
wrong so basically everyone say I can
also see you guys all it's you you're
the most part did really well so
so I'm pleased to see that this stuff is
is for the most part you guys have seen
it and I assume that anyone who got a
romancer is more just to the misfit time
it's and so what will keep this is an
experiment I know that people use this
technology successful in classes so I
want to give it a chance to sort of but
it shake out so getting back to the
matters at hand then there's a sort of
quirky question Mike and see
and see it's possible when you just say
int it's a a signed number can be
positive potentially can be negative on
most machines but not all not guaranteed
it would be represented as a two's
complement numbers it can alter the
quitter a a a datatype an unsigned
datatype implicitly it will be an int
it's redundant but you can also say
unsigned int so I can can't use casting
ah to convert from a two's complement
number to a unsigned number and you can
imagine various conventions like one of
the when you might imagine about this
would be implemented to say well minus
one is a negative number and I can't
represent that it's an unsigned number
but I could give me a zero and it's all
me off by one should be good enough
through partial present right so you
might think that's what it would do but
it does it does anyone know in what on
most machines this value will be what
you will end up being yes almost two to
the thirty one that's it's actually 2 to
the 32nd minus 1 right it's like if you
imagine an unsigned number of all ones
which is what minus one looks like
that's the number that it will be so
that's the right idea so yes exactly
that's the main idea and it's kind of a
weird idea to think about but in demo
what happens when you cast and see
between signed and unsigned
is nothing the bits just stay the same
it's just all of a sudden I think of
that I order bits either positive or
negative weight depending on whether I'm
thinking about it is signed or unsigned
but nothing changes
it's a bit like really a way different
idea but if I say it's a low cover
14-point a week from today if I say
something is a floating-point number and
then I convert it to an int then
something really happens the bits really
change and that's actually a fairly
important concept but for now we'll
disconnect well keep track of these this
special case of between unsigned and
signed this is truancy and in both
southern languages that support an
unsigned datatype so this idea is you
know logically what we can think of it
is we're going to take a number that's
potentially negative and morph it into
one that's definitely not negative but
the rule we're going to do is basically
to keep the bits the same and really
just change the numerical value
associated with them and the same is
true in the reverse direction so if we
look at our little table going left to
right or right to well if they're both
in the range where the high order bit is
0 then the numeric values are the same
but if we're going in the range where
the high order bit isn't one then we're
either increasing
decreasing the number by sixteen or two
to the W in this case and what that
means from a certain pictorial point of
view is we're taking the the green range
of numbers the smaller or magnitude
numbers and where we're keeping them the
same but the numbers that were very
negative before become very positive now
and then the same is in the reverse
direction in the other way and then this
actually can have some kind of strange
behaviors as a result and in fact it can
lead to some some really unpleasant
results if you're not aware of it or
prepared for it
and in fact you'll find in some
languages like Java does not even have
an unsigned datatype because there's so
many carols at that time so as I've been
showing with my notation you can
explicitly do casting to convert but
that's also what's called implicit
casting for example if I have EC on the
bottom they if I just say you act some
unsigned value and I assign it to a
signed in it will do this it's implicit
casting and of course in this case
nothing really happens because the bits
stay the same but logically I'm
converting in some way between an
unsigned number and a signed number here
without anything being obvious that
that's going on similarly you can have a
function that takes an unsigned argument
and casted a signed value it might
return a signed value and you could
assign it to an unsigned value and those
are all casts that get applied
automatically from one feel
and so again that can cause some
confusion just to give you a suti
illustration of of why this can matter
one of the the quirks of the language
that I don't know why they came up with
this convention but they did is if
you're doing any operations where one
argument is a sign that the other is
unsigned then the row is you
automatically convert that sign number
to an unsigned one and then continue the
operation and that applies to addition
multiplication and things but also to
comparison operations like less than and
greater than so just to illustrate what
I'm talking about these examples show
some what might be surprising results
and I'll mention in see again that
anything you write as a decimal number
is by default signed unless he put at
you that can be their upper or lowercase
u at the end of it so for example if I'm
comparing zero the sign number to zero
the unsigned number what would the
relative values of those be well they're
equal right because they're both if you
think of it think of their bit patterns
they're all zeros and anytime for all
the numbers reasonably close to zero
there's no difference between the
unsigned in two's complement
representation and you'll see on the the
right-hand side it's key to understand
how is this expression evaluated and so
what's really happening is since this
right-hand argument is a expressed
explicitly as an unsigned number I'm
infinitely going to cast this
to an unsigned number do the comparison
so if I compare minus 1 to 0 it will be
less greater or equal that's right
obviously but what if now I put a little
you on that zero
I didn't change the bits remember it's
gonna quit there what's going on it's
flipping because remember if I turn a
minus one into an unsigned number which
I will for this comparison because
there's an unsigned on birds here their
argument all of a sudden that minus 1
becomes and so it will become a very
large number compared to 0 that will be
greater what if I compare this we
recognize his TV in and this will
recognize it I'm tight this is Tmax
biggest its complement number and this
is team n the most negative cheese
complement number what the relation will
between that greater right it's positive
number is greater than oh but what if I
put in you
yes be like so in this case it's gonna
try it see if this works I don't really
have like a blank sheet of paper though
so anyways what's giving away all the
cool stuff but this one's pretty
important remember that
it's what I want to do and this one the
bit pattern is a one followed by a bunch
of zeros and so if it's a unsigned
comparison then the left one is smaller
than the right but if it's a sign
comparison then the last part is a
positive number and the right one is a
negative number and so it's and and
soco's you can see these other examples
are all instances of them
so this always sort of a abstract thing
like so it's it's actually a really good
source of exam questions but I won't let
you worry about it
quite yet but it actually is a risk that
happens in your life programs that when
you start using unsigned there are
certain things that you might be
accustomed to that you no longer can do
so for example imagine I have an
unsigned loop variable I and I wanted to
do a countdown I want to keep basically
what's called up some I want to take the
values of an array and keep adding
backward back to a of zero and keep
accumulating the values backwards so
what's wrong with this program it's like
seriously wrong in every it's an
infinite write the logic waits an
infinite loop because I is always going
to be greater equals zero I said in time
so what happens is I will hit zero and
then you'll decrement it and what number
will you get when you go what whole
decrementing zero give you an unsigned
number yeah you max exactly give you a
bunch of ones so often a of I is going
to be at an address it actually doesn't
exist on any machine that's been built
as if yet because there are no true 64
well no it would exist on some Lucien
exactly but it's a really big number and
chances arts and out of bounds of your
memory region and it will hit what's
called a segmentation fault but so
probably just crash as opposed to run in
an infinite loop but in any case it
won't do what was intended so you look
at that you go yaha you're kind of what
do you expect
you should never say I greater equal to
zero because anyone can tell that's
never going to happen
it can be much more subtle than that
though like way more so here's an
example suppose somewhere I have this a
number I've defined it somewhere as
because I don't want to keep using size
though all over the place so I just call
it Delta and I want to do the same
general count down trick something in
this same way I want to keep working
this down and so within some range close
to zero but Delta is a positive numbers
so I'm not actually gonna ever let I go
below zero and I was assigned number in
the first place so that should be fine
so yeah you might want to guess what
happens with this go yeah right very
good
so there's a couple things going on here
if you think about it the NC sizeof
operator which is a pretty important
operator it returns a value of type size
underscore T and that's defined on all
machines to be an unsigned number that
sort of big enough to hold an arbitrary
a range of values for for a data type so
it would be either to the 32 on it when
you're running 32 bits or two to the 64
range but the point is it's an unsigned
note it's always an unsigned note and so
Delta is unsigned and now as you just
said so when I subtract Delta from I I
do this implicit casting trick and so
the result will be unsigned even though
it started with a sign
and I subtracted a constant from it all
of a sudden it magically into the eyes
of the C language becomes an unsigned
number and so it's the same problem as
before it's never less than zero and so
it gets into the same problem as before
so my point being that these kind of and
it's the kind of bug that you can stare
at this for hours because mentally it's
hard to remember this particular quirk
of the language and so these are
especially difficult types of bugs to
deal okay
well we'll keep on looking at these sort
of different representations and what
they mean oh so as I've mentioned before
they we see already cases where we have
some things or eight debts some things
you sixteen summer thirty-two and summer
sixty-four and so there's quite a few
operations it for one reason another
have to a go between those different
sizes and so the general rule for at
least for the sign numbers from going
from a smaller representation to larger
one is to do what's called the sign
extension which again often might not
seem like a very useful thing but the
idea of sign extension when you're going
from a smaller word size to larger one
is if you keep replicating that leftmost
or sign bit and the reason for doing
that is with this two's complement
representation what it will do is it
will preserve numeric values so just as
an example if I'm taking a five bit
number and expand it to a sixty-six bit
number if that number is positive I just
want to stick a zero in because I'm just
and you can obviously that won't make a
difference but the point is that's
actually a form of a sign extent I'm
taking the leftmost bit
and I'm copying it which makes no real
obvious difference for the positive case
but you see it's also the right thing to
do on the negative case then if I
replicate that -16 should be what
success what do people think
right I want minus 16 plus 4 plus 2 is
better
oh my god so I didn't make up this way
it's actually kind of cute this example
is actually a pretty interesting to
think about the logic behind this so I
want to make sure that the details are
right but look at the this case here you
see what happened is in this 5 bit
number the most significant bit had a
weight of -16 and when it becomes a
6-bit number that -16 flips be positive
16 but on adding another fifth year with
weight - 32 and so both of those are
ones you see it kind of cancels out that
it cancels out with the net result of
minus 16 and you think about oh yeah
that's actually the general principle
behind it and this sign extension you
can sign you can work it out that you
can sign extend as far left as you want
and you'll get the same result that here
introducing a string of bits whose total
weight sum together is equal to the
single
earlier number and so that's the logic
between sign extension of of how you go
from a sign number to a larger sign
number without changing the numeric
values and that's what happens when you
cast say from a short of care to an int
it will do that sign extension in order
to preserve the value there's other
times when we want to kind of squish
things down we want to take a bigger
number and reduce the number of gets one
thing you'll think about is first is
wait a minute you can't do that
that's what quad Chanin's information
theory told me is you know there's
certain amount of information and you
can't go any smaller and that's right so
what happens is somehow we're going to
potentially lose information here it can
be even worse than that we can not only
lose something but we can come up with
something that seems to have nothing to
do with the earlier value but that's
what happens when we go from a larger
number to smaller one and in general uh
so for example it if we're going from a
five bit number down to four and it's a
signed number what we're doing is we're
taking that sign bit that was before and
we're basically tossing that away and
whatever it happens to be and now the
new a most significant position all of a
sudden positive weight to a negative
weight and if the numbers are closing up
to zero you'll see that that actually is
just fine whether it's negative or
positive I can basically afford to lose
that most significant day and still
maintain my numeric value just like sort
of the inverse of the sign extension
operation on the other hand if if I
if the the number I'm dropping is not
the same bit value is the new sign bit
then I'm actually going to sort of do
strange changes so for example this is
10 that one's correct but if I make this
a 4 bit number mysterious so it's going
to become minus 6 but it's going to
decrease by 16 and similarly if I take a
negative number which is which is minus
10 they got this one right and I drop
off that that it's gonna become 6 and
the reason of course is I can't
represent minus 10 as a four-bit 2's
complement number my range is between
minus 8 and positive 7 in this
representation and so what I did was
basically flip it so the point being
that when you lose information you can
you're just gonna change how you think
about these bits and it may or may not
be the right thing to do unless the
numbers already fairly close cos you're
on
ok then we'll do this for today